<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise concerning a Christians carefull abstinence from all appearance of evill gathered for the most part out of the schoolemen, and casuists: wherein the questions and cases of conscience belonging unto the difficult matter of scandall are briefly resolved: By Henry Jeanes, Mr of Arts, lately of Hart-Hall in Oxon, and rector of the church of Beere-Crocombe in Somerset-shire.</title>
            <author>Jeanes, Henry, 1611-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 158 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04365</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14480</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103351</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839107</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839107</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3506</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04365)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3506)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1244:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise concerning a Christians carefull abstinence from all appearance of evill gathered for the most part out of the schoolemen, and casuists: wherein the questions and cases of conscience belonging unto the difficult matter of scandall are briefly resolved: By Henry Jeanes, Mr of Arts, lately of Hart-Hall in Oxon, and rector of the church of Beere-Crocombe in Somerset-shire.</title>
                  <author>Jeanes, Henry, 1611-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 151, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Turner for H. Curteine,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page 142: page number printed upside down.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Abstinence from all appearance of evill in practice.</note>
                  <note>Errata on verso of G6, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Page 88 stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Good and evil --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scandals --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3506:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3506:1"/>
            <p>A TREATISE Concerning A CHRISTIANS CAREFULL AB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence from all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Evill: Gathered FOR THE MOST part out of the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Caſuiſts:</p>
            <p>Wherein The Queſtions and Caſes of Conſcience belonging unto the difficult matter of Scandall are briefly reſolved:</p>
            <p>By HENRY JEANES, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of Arts, lately of <hi>Hart-Hall</hi> in OXON, and Rector of the Church of <hi>Beere-Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combe</hi> in <hi>Somerſet-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by W. TURNER for H. CURTEINE 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3506:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3506:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>HONORATISSIMO PHILIPPO Comiti Pem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brochiae, &amp; Montgom: Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriſſimi Ordinis periſcelidis E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiti: Regiae Familiae Archica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merario: nec non Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtau Regiae à ſecretiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Conſiliis, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoratiſſime Comes,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Gnoſcar, precor, lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus honor, tam ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenni tanti nominis convicio, &amp; impunè liceat auguſtam illam &amp; praenobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem titulorum ſeriem vili huic, &amp; alioqui periturae, chartulae praefigere. Ea ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidem obſcura eſt Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris ſimul &amp; Operis infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, ut prorſus metuat ſine validiore praeſidio in publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum prodire, &amp; perenni gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deat lucis fugâ, ni precario &amp; praepotente potiatur fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voris
<pb facs="tcp:3506:3"/>radio: veſtro ſc, qui malignos quoſcunque Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticorum halitus cohibere valet, &amp; praetenues haſce ſtudiorum Primitias Laetio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri meſſe ſecundare. Aggre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur, ſat ſcio, parvulus hic Liber, materiam lubricam &amp; ancipitem, de abſtinentia ab omni ſpecie mali, ſeu de fuga ſcandali, verendumq, eſt, ne apud Cenſores duri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſculos ſcandalu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſibi creet, &amp; faſtidium. Attamen qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, qualis eſt, tuo ſtipatus patrocinio ſecurè prodit, nec iniqua moratur malevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum ſcandala, modò ne ſit dignitati veſtrae juſto of fendiculo.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Amplitudini tuae Sacel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanus, &amp; Servus omni of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficii genere obſtrictus, HEN: JEANES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3506:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. THESS: 22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Abſtaine from all appearance of Evill.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR Apoſtle directs us, in the Verſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this Text, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Good,</hi> in this Text con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Evill.</hi> Towards <hi>Good</hi> hee exacts a <hi>prudent warineſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> towards <hi>Evill,</hi> a <hi>ſcrupulous fearfulneſſe:</hi> towards <hi>good,</hi> a prudent warineſſe; <hi>Prove all things,</hi> and then, <hi>hold faſt that which is good.</hi> Nothing, how colourable ſoever is to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved hand over head, before tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and examination by the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of the Sanctuarie: for, <hi>Vitia virtutes mentiuntur,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi>) vice is mask't under the skinne of vertue, falſhood
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3506:4"/>diſguiſ'd under the face of truth: ſo that the one is often miſtaken for the other. The groſſeſt enormities have beene glaſt and coloured over with the names, and face of vertues; the moſt poyſonous hereſies have often gained the eſteeme and applauſe of Orthodoxe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents: and therefore as we muſt ſted faſtly retaine that which is truly true and good; ſo muſt we prudently diſcerne and carefully diſtinguiſh between that which is ſown <hi>deed, and in truth,</hi> and that which is ſo only <hi>in ſhew,</hi> &amp; <hi>colour;</hi> this we muſt reject, that keepe, and hold faſt. <hi>Prove all things, hold faſt that which is good.</hi> But he requires now to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards evill a farre different car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: there hee lookes for a <hi>ſcrupulous fearfulneſſe.</hi> Though we muſt not hold faſt any thing that hath but the appearance of good, yet wee muſt abſtaine from but the appearance of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3506:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſtaine from all appearance of evill;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cor. Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pide.</note> or from every evill ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance: the words are and may be rendred indifferently, either way, both rendrings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equally conſonant to the truth, and originall.</p>
            <p>In the words our Apoſtle meetes with a cavill, riſe among the Libertines of our and former times, who when their ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous courſes are charged upon them, baffle of all with this plea; that they are not intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecally ſinfull. Could I (will the profaneſt Libertine ſay) but once fee ſuch and ſuch things proved in themſelves to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull: why, I would make no more words of the matter, but ſoone forbeate them. I, but have they the bluſh, the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of evill? that ſhould be motive enough to ſhun them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abſtaine from all, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But are wee ſure this is the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles meaning? are not the words capable of another inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation?
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3506:5"/>Firſt, ſome miſlike our tranſlation of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>species,</hi> by appearance, &amp; rather thinke it ſhould be meant logically, for ſort or kinde, and ſo the words thus rendred: Abſtaine from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſort, or kind of evill. That it may be ſo, <hi>Mat. Flac. Illiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> determines that it is ſoe, the Syriacke interpreter, and after him <hi>Faber,</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve. But I would faine know upon what ground they are thus ſingular againſt the current of both Ancient, and Moderne Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors. Setting aſide this place, the word occurres (as I thinke) in the whole new Teſtament but foure times, In <hi>Luke</hi> 3.22.9.29. <hi>John</hi> 5.37.2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. and in none of theſe places is it, can it be taken in a Logicall no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. If not elſewhere, why here? eſpecially ſeeing ſuch an exception is not inforced by the ſcope, coherence, any other circumſtance of the Text, or any abſurditie otherwiſe unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3506:5"/>
            <p>But ſome dreame of a foule abſurditie, that would enſue upon tranſlating <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>species,</hi> appearance. If every appearance of evill ſhould be abſtained from, then ſhould good things, the beſt things be eſchewed, for they commonly appeare to be evill unto ſenſe, and carnall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that diſcerne not the things of the ſpirit of God. How eaſily may an acute wit ſet falſe faces upon them, &amp; worke a bad conceit of them into ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ill or weake apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>This feare will quickly vaniſh and be diſcovered to be idle, and vaine, when anon we ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine that diſtinction of appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of evill, into <hi>reall</hi> and <hi>ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginarie;</hi> for the preſent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, leaving theſe men, proceed we ſecondly, to others, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with us in interpreting <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in a vulgar, familiar, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſenſe, for appearance: but then their expoſition is not ſo
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3506:6"/>generall, as ours; for they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine the place to matters of doctrine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and will not allow it to be extended to matters of practice; &amp; countenance they thinke the context gives their gloſſe, for the Apoſtle having at the 19. verſe exhorted not to quench the ſpirit, in verſe 20. preſcribes a meanes for cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Spirit, <hi>viz:</hi> a reverent demeanour towards the Word of God. If ye will not quench the Spirit, <hi>deſpiſe not prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> and next: leaſt that ſome ſhould except: are we thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verently to receive promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly all prophecyings, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines preached unto us,
<note place="margin">Heming<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> and not to beware of ſome, of falſe prophecying and doctrines, the Apoſtle, ſay they, more diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly directs, how wee ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meane our ſelves. Firſt, towards all prophecying in generall: how, ſecondly, towards true; how, thirdly, towards falſe. Firſt, all prophecyings, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3506:6"/>whatſoever muſt be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently examined. <hi>Prove all things.</hi> Secondly, all true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecyings, ſound, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoxe doctrines are to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced with a firme, and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable aſſent. <hi>Hold faſt that which is good.</hi> Laſtly, as for falſe prophecyings &amp; doctrines even their very appearance is to be ſhunned. Thus they, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But firſt, I propoſe unto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the learned, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no an exact and accurate coherence be to be looked for in moſt of thoſe precepts deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by the Apoſtle, from verſe 13. <hi>uſque ad</hi> verſ. 23. the looſe and abrupt manner of heaping them together perſwade, (mee thinks) that there is little depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> upon ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the foregoing or following precepts, as is to be expected betweene <hi>Solomons</hi> Proverbs, or <hi>Bede's</hi> Axiomes. Hence is it that <hi>Eſtius</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Neque neceſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> eſt hanc par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> (ut qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dam f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt)<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ut connexio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> tis, quae proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt: nam po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ùs vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolus r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>care me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriam e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus, quod pracepi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cap. ſup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors; ut h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>neſts ambulent ad eos, que foris ſun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</hi> Eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> holds it not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to interpret the place ſo, as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3506:7"/>that it ſhould have connexion with thoſe duties that immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately precede; rather (thinkes hee) the Apoſtle ſeemes to rub up the memorie of what hee comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the former chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, at verſ. 12. That ye may walke honeſtly towards them that are without.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſuppoſe a cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the words with the former, muſt it needs be that which they obtrude. The words may ſit under our inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, and yet the Analyſis of the Context runne ſmoothly, as thus:</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle having at verſ. 19. dehorted from quenching the Spirit, next adviſeth uſe of meanes, tending to the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of its gratious &amp; glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reſidence in the Soule: Which meanes are either nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, or poſitive; hee aſſignes but one negative meanes, <hi>viz<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> a removall of a maine barre, &amp; powerfull obſtacle unto the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3506:7"/>preſence of the Spirit, contempt of preaching. <hi>Despiſe not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecying,</hi> verſe 20. of the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive means, two concerne good, one evill: the two concerning good,
<note place="margin">Aquinas in locum.</note> are <hi>boni diligens examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, conſtans electio: Prove all things, hold fast that which is good.</hi> This reſpecting evill, <hi>eſt univerſaliſſima ejus rejectio,</hi> an abſtinence not onely from all kinds, but even from all appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of evill.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, ſuppoſe the primarie ſcope and intention of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle be limited unto matters of doctrine: yet becauſe the maine reaſon, for which they themſeves conceive appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of evill, even in matters of doctrine to be interdicted, is avoidance of Scandall, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of which is <hi>juris Natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis,</hi> and not onely doctrines but alſo actions are ſcandalous; juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therefore unto theſe, as well as thoſe, is the text appliable, and applyed too, by all Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3506:8"/>or others that ever I met with purpoſely treating on the point of Scandall. Should we then againſt the more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally receiv'd opinion of either former or later times, admit of their narrow, and curtail'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation for the cleare, and indubitate ſenſe of the Apoſtle? Yet to make the wordes more inſtructive, their uſe more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, wee might warrantably put an enlargement Logicians call it an ampliation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) upon them, and extend them <hi>ad mores,</hi> as well as <hi>ad dogmata; ad agenda,</hi> as well as <hi>ad credenda;</hi> to the <hi>decalogue,</hi> as well as <hi>creed,</hi> not onely to do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinall truths, but morall duties alſo.</p>
            <p>Uſe of a diviſion here is none, but to bewray Logicke: and therefore without more adoe wee will roundly betake our ſelves to Limitation, Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Application of the plaine point here commended to us: wee are to abſtaine not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3506:8"/>onely from things intrinſecally ſinfull, but from all ſhews, and appearances of ſinne.</p>
            <p>For limitation,
<note n="1" place="margin">Limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> appearance of evill is either in <hi>poſitions,</hi> or <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then, 'tis queſtioned, whether or no wee are to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from all poſitions, which have an appearance of evill: of falſhood.</p>
            <p>For reſolution wee muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Concerning appearance of evill in <hi>poſitions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Concerning abſtinence fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch an appearance.</p>
            <p>Appearance of Evill in <hi>Poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> is twofold,</p>
            <p n="1">1 Either in regard of their <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>ſubſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Or elſe in the <hi>termes,</hi> and <hi>expreſſions</hi> uſed in their propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall.</p>
            <p>That which is in regard of their matter and ſubſtance, is, either to <hi>our ſelves,</hi> or <hi>others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, to diſtinguiſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3506:9"/>abſtinence from the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Evill, or falſhoud in Poſitions: we may be ſaid to abſtaine from doctrines falſe in appearance, two manner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of wayes: either</p>
            <p n="1">1 When wee abſtaine from <hi>aſſenting</hi> to them.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or when we abſtaine from <hi>publiſhing</hi> of them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Wee abſtaine from aſſenting to them, either <hi>Poſitively,</hi> or <hi>Negatively.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poſitively,</hi> when by a poſitive and reall act of the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding we diſſent from, we reject them. Now diſſent from them is twofold.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Either abſolute and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorie.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Or elſe but conditionall, &amp; cautionary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Negatively,</hi> when we do not diſſent from them, but only not <hi>aſſent</hi> unto them: when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſuſpend our aſſent.</p>
            <p>To apply theſe diſtinctions.</p>
            <p>Note firſt, that though the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3506:9"/>ſubſtance or matter of doctrines appeare to be falſe unto our ſelves, our owne judgements, yet are we not bound to abſtain poſitively from aſſenting to them, to diſſent from them, to reject them; for this appearance may not be true &amp; reall, groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the doctrines them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which perhaps may not ſend forth the leaſt colour or ſhadow for ſuſpicion, but onely put and faſtned upon them by means of the errour, ignorance, and darkeneſſe of our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings that perhaps not with due care and circumſpection, but rather with much precipitancie have given their cenſure of them; and therefore however at firſt bluſh they ſeeme falſe, yet when once the light of our reaſon is cleared from miſts, and clouds, they may upon due exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination prove true; and to diſſent from, and reject a truth would be a foule errour of, and blemiſh to our underſtanding.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:3506:10"/>
            <p>Oblig'd wee are then, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine, not <hi>poſitively,</hi> but <hi>nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively,</hi> from aſſenting to them; that is, not to <hi>diſſent</hi> from them, but only not to <hi>aſſent</hi> unto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to <hi>ſtay</hi> our <hi>aſſent,</hi> to demurre a while, before wee give in our judgement leaſt we receive any thing with a doubtfull, entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled, and perplexed conſoience. Of this <hi>Calvin</hi> gives us an hint in his expoſition on this place, <hi>Speci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> mali interpretor, cùm nondum it a comperta eſt doctrinae falſitas, at meritò rejici quent, ſed tamen aliqua haeret ſiniſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuſpicio, &amp; timetur, we quid ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neni lateat: ergò ab eo genere do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinae, quod malum, etiamſinon ſit, apparet, abſtinere praecipit, non quod in totum rejici permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat, ſed quia recipi, aut fidem ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinere non debet. Cur enim pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ùs quod bonum eſt teneri juſſit, nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oabſtinere vult, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſimpliciter à malo, ſed à mali specie? quia ubi dijudicatione in luce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta fuerit veritas, tunc demùm <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3506:10"/>fide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haberi decet; ubi aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubeſt falſi metus, aut mens dubitatione eſt implicita, pedem referre, vel grad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuſpendere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>venit, ne quid dubiâ perplexâ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ntiâ am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plectamur.</hi> By the appearance of evill I underſtand (faith he) when as the falſhood of a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is not yet ſo throughly detected, that it may be deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly rejected, but yet there ſtickes ſome bad ſuſpition of it, &amp; 'tis feared, leaſt poyſon lurke under it: therefore he comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds us to abſtaine from that hind of doctrine, which though it be not evill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet appeares ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not as though it ought altogether to be rejected but becauſe it ought not to be received, to be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. For why doth hee before command us to hold faſt onely that which is good, and here he wills us to abſtaine not barely from evill, but from its appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance? becauſe when after a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough ſifting a truth is cleared, 'tis fitting it ſhould forthwith
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3506:11"/>be believed: but when as the falſhood of it is feared, or the mind with doubting is entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled, we muſt for a while with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw our aſſent, leaſt wee em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace any thing with a doubting and perplexed conſcience.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe I for mine owne part am firmly perſwaded of the truth of ſuch, or ſuch a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, or at leaſt unconvinced, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſwaded of its falſhood, and yet it appeare generally unto unto others to bee falſe the judgements, of the godly lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, of moſt of the ancient Fathers, unto either generall or provinciall Councels: in ſuch a caſe what courſe muſt I take, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath appearance of falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood unto others underſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dings, muſt I therefore diſſent from it, or ſtoppe mine aſſent unto it?</p>
            <p>For anſwer, take theſe foure following rules.</p>
            <p>Firſt, wee owe ſo reverent &amp; humble an eſteeme of, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion unto the Spirits of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3506:11"/>Prophets, to the judgement of learned, ſober, &amp; pious Divines, unto the writings of the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent godly Fathers, unto the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and decrees of Occumeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and Provinciall Councels, at that whatſoever Tenents the whole Church repreſentative, to wit, a generall Councell, or the greateſt and cheefeſt part of the Church moſt of the Fathers and Divines too, of later and preſent times, have rejected, &amp; condemned for falſe, and erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous, we ſhould abſtaine nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively from aſſenting to, that is, though not change, yet ſuſpend our beleefe of them, and not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſe over our full and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute aſſent unto them, untill by diligent inquiſition, fervent prayer, imploring the guidance of Gods holy Spirit, and uſe of all other good meanes, either their conſonancie with, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonancie from the truth, be cleerly diſcerned, fully confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and manifeſted unto our conſciences.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:3506:12"/>
            <p>But Chriſtian modeſtie ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not here, but goeth one ſtep further, and in a ſecond place exacts of us a conditionall, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable,
<note place="margin">Dr Jack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</note> and cautionary diſſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all doctrines thus generally ſuſpected, and cenſured: For upon generall diſlike of a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, as upon a prudentiall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, wee may ground a ſtrong preſumption, an high and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable conjecture of the falſhood of it; ſo that hereupon we may reject it, though not in an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and irrevocable way, yet with this limitation &amp; caution; ſo the apparent veritie therein of it ſelfe do not force us to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it. So ſottiſh I am not, as to meaſure truth by multitude of voices: for errours I know that have grated upon the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, nay hereſies, that have razed the foundation, have had their cloud of witneſſes; yet I ſhould ſo farre honor a publike teſtimonie, as to ſuſpect mine owne and others private bare
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3506:12"/>opinions, (not back't by plaine Scripture, with evident ſenſe, or a full demonſtrative argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,) rather than a generall ſuffrage: For, <hi>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mo omnes, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem omnes fefellêre,</hi> improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as for one to deceive all, ſo for all to deceive one:
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nec du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitamus, coeteris quidem pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, &amp;c.</hi> Rivett: I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſag. ad Scrip. Sact. cap. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Rivet</hi> is a man bred up in ſuch a Church, as it is not likely that he ſhould aſcribe overmuch to Church Councels, or Miniſters, and yet he makes no doubt, but <hi>coeter is paribus,</hi> that is, if parts, prayer, diligence of ſtudie after the truth, bee equall, that then a greater and fuller meaſure of the gift of expounding the Scripture, and deciding contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies thereabouts, is commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to the publicke Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Church, (whether they execute their function ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally, and apart in ſome one particular Church, or elſe joint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conferre, and diſcourſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves concerning the true and genuine ſenſe of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3506:13"/>the Scriptures in ſome aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies call'd lawfully, and in the name of Chriſt) than unto ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall private men, who were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther endowed with ſo many gifts, nor ſee with ſo many eyes, nor by their private and ſingle meditation can equall the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted conſultations and enquiries after truth of many. And thus you ſee how farre Chriſtian mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty requireth us to abſtaine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſſenting to doctrines upon the appearance of evill, of falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, which they carry unto thoſe, who in interpreting Scripture, and deciding contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, have committed to them the publicke office of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and inſtruction of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: but yet it taketh not from us the judgement of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate diſcretion; for Chriſtian libertie alloweth us ſuch a free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of diſſenting unto what the Church, or her chiefe, and publicke Miniſters ſay, as it is to be ſpecified in the next two following rules.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:3506:13"/>
            <p>In a third place therefore, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Church, or the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and chiefeſt part of her, charge errour &amp; falſhood upon ſuch a doctrine; yet this bare and ſingle teſtimonie, not ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by any Scripture or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, is not to gaine ſo farre upon our beliefe, as that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon wee ſhould preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and diſſent from the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine thus generally cenſured with an abſolute and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie diſſent. This were to give unto the Churches deciſions as high an over-ruling a ſuffrage in our harts, as is onely due to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine revelations: to receive them, not as they are indeed the word of men, but as if they were the word of God: to yeeld unto them an abſolute divine faith, and credence. This were a meere <hi>Vaſſallage</hi> of our ſoules, underſtandings, faiths, unto the authority of an humaine teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie: a thing utterly unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the generoſitie &amp; freedome
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3506:14"/>of Chriſtian Spirits. If God hath indulged to any the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of ſuch dominion over mens faiths, and conſciences: alas! then to what purpoſe hath hee placed that glorious lampe of reaſon in our boſomes? of what uſe are our <hi>intellectualls?</hi> what place is there left for S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls proving of all things,</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John's triall of the Spirits?</hi>
               <note n="1" place="margin">Joh. 4.1.</note> but the truth is, that God is ſo farre from enſlaving our underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, or captivating our beliefe unto the judgement of any mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, as that hee approves not onely of a forbearance from a flat, and abſolute <hi>diſſent</hi> from doubtfull doctrines thus pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickely, and generally diſliked, but alſo of a full &amp; peremptorie aſſent unto doctrines manifeſtly true, though condemned in a generall Councel, as is apparent from the fourth and laſt rule, which is:</p>
            <p>If a doctrine bee as true in it ſelfe, ſo alſo clearely, and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3506:14"/>by mee apprehended to be ſo, and yet appeare generally to be falſe unto others, of what degree, order, or condition ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: nevertheleſſe it commands abſolute ſubſcription and aſſent of the minde without <hi>contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> without <hi>heſitancie,</hi> nay without ſo much as <hi>ſuſpenſe</hi> of judgement. If the veritie then of a Doctrine bee apparent, it muſt over-rule the aſſent of the underſtanding againſt the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of the whole world. For the teſtimony of men, of the wiſeſt, holyeſt men conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered either apart, or as aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in a Councell, admits as all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies of examination, and triall by the ballance of the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and rules of right reaſon, ſo likewiſe of contradiction and denyall, when in it there is an expreſſe, and evident variation from either reaſon, or divine authoritie. In ſuch a caſe wee may lawfully, &amp; ſafely diſſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it; alwaies provided, that it be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3506:15"/>not in an inſolent manner, but with a reverent, child-like, and reſpectfull baſhfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>But to goe on, if I am not to abſtaine from aſſenting to a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine minifeſtly true, becauſe it appeares generally to others to be falſe, muſt I not yet abſtaine from <hi>publiſhing,</hi> from <hi>ſpreading</hi> of it, either by writing or prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching?</p>
            <p>For anſwer, thou muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the generall nature, and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the doctrine, thus wrongly either <hi>accuſed,</hi> or <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected</hi> of <hi>falſhood,</hi> and alſo of what uſe and importance it is in regard of the preſent times and places, wherein thou liveſt, and if it prove to be a doctrine <hi>fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall,</hi> of <hi>abſolute neceſſitie</hi> to <hi>faith</hi> or <hi>manners,</hi> then that of <hi>Gregory</hi> may take place: <hi>Si de veritate ſcandalum ſumatur.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi>) <hi>melius eſt,
<note place="margin">Sept. Hom. in Eze:</note> ut ſcandalum oriatur, quàm ut ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas relinquatur.</hi> As alſo that of <hi>Calvin: Quemadmodum enim</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:3506:15"/>(faith <hi>Calvin</hi>) <hi>Charitati ſubjici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda eſt noſtra libertas,
<note place="margin">Cal. lib. 3. Inſt. c. 12. ſect. 13.</note> ita ſub fidei puritate ſubſidere viciſſim charitas ipſa debet:</hi> as our liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is to be ſubjected to charity, ſo alſo our very charitie it ſelfe to faiths puritie.</p>
            <p>But now if it be a <hi>Doctrine,</hi> either not <hi>fundamentall,</hi> but of a lower <hi>rank</hi> &amp; <hi>quality,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in both orthodoxe writers, and preachers may vary and abound in their owne ſenſe without prejudice to the foundation; or if it be of ſo ſmall uſe, that upon its divulgement, it is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable there will ariſe ſo much honour to God, and edification of the Church, as may <hi>prepon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate</hi> thoſe <hi>miſchiefes,</hi> that hurly-burly, thoſe tumults, and contentions in the Church, which in all likelyhood will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue thereby, thou muſt then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to vent it, either from Preſſe, or Pulpit; ſo ſhalt thou beſt conſult for thine owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate quiet, and publicke peace.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3506:16"/>And wee muſt follow after things that make for <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>edification: Rom.</hi> 14.19. About ſuch matters to be contentious wee have no cuſtome, nor the Churches of God: and indeed about them to be contentious were the right pranke of a <hi>Schiſmaticke;</hi> for not onely he is a Schiſmaticke (ſaith
<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Non enìm ſchiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus eò ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcitur, quòd fovet perverſum dogma, i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mò contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git aliqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, ut ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> minis ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſsima ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quia eam neque loco, neque te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, nullà<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitate ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticus eſt, et ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalum ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecit Des populo; cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m non agatur ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, oſtendit ſe non ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio gloria Chriſts, ſed ſuae pottùs ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bâſſe.</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meron in ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctiora quaedam N. T. loca Tom. 2. in Mat. c. 18. v. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi>) who maintaines a perverſe Tenent; a man may hold a very true opinion, and yet play the Schiſmaticke, and give ſcandall unto the people of God by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering it in a raſh, unpeace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and unſeaſonable manner, neither in fit place, nor due time, no neceſſitie urging thereunto; for ſeeing in determining of his opinion the glory of God, and weale of the Church lye not at the ſtake, hee plainly ſhewes, that hee hath troubled the Church, lead with deſire of not Chriſts glory, but his owne cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. I confeſſe indeed, that a controverted, and ſuſpected
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3506:16"/>truth even of this low qualitie may be peaceably, and modeſtly profeſſed, and debated too in private, but a publicke promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation thereof is at any hand to be forborne, <hi>non ſub intuitu ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, ſed minoris boni,</hi> not under the apprehenſion of any evill in the truth, but onely as a leſſer good, which will not conſiſt with a greater, the tranquilitie of the Church; or if you will, the publicke promulgation of ſuch a truth is to be forborne, <hi>ſub Intuitu Mali, etſi non Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliciter, tamen per Accidens ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis:</hi> under the apprehenſion of evill, not in the controverted truth, but in the promulgation thereof, which though it be not <hi>ſimply</hi> evill, yet becomes <hi>acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentally</hi> ſo, to wit, by compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, in reſpect of a <hi>greater good</hi> then required, preſervation of the generall quiet; with which for the preſent it cannot ſtand, unto the care of which it is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed though not <hi>primo &amp; per
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3506:17"/>ſe,</hi> yet <hi>ex conſequenti conne xione virtutum,</hi> as <hi>Suarez</hi> upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſion acutely phraſeth it. But I digreſſe.</p>
            <p>To goe on to that appearance of evill in doctrines, which is in the <hi>expreſſions</hi> uſed in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſall, a thing I could wiſh it were not too rife amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who like no truth, unleſſe delivered in <hi>hereticall teaermes;</hi> men wonderfully taken with the language of <hi>Aſhdod,</hi> the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh dialect.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In rebus fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei verba debent eſse caſta, &amp; exacta, &amp; quae rem ipſam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priè expri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant, &amp; haereticis non praeſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t occaſionem calumn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onds.</hi> Pet. Martinez:</note> But let it be our care to refraine all words and phraſes, which carry an appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of either hereſie or ſchiſme; for though they may, and are by us meant in an orthodoxe ſenſe, yet carry they a ſhrewd ſhew of evill, make others jealous, and ſuſpicious of our ſoundneſſe. And therefore
<note n="*" place="margin">Lib. 12. de locis cap. 9. ad tertium.</note> 
               <hi>Canus</hi> although he will by no meanes aſſent, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely to that uſuall ſaying; <hi>ex verbis inordinatè pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atis fit ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſis;</hi> yet hee is content to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of it, if it be moderated
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3506:17"/>with this caution, <hi>ſecundn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptionem audientium, &amp; judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, qui per exteriora ſigna de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent judicare de haereſi:</hi> if it be underſtood according to the ſuppoſall of hearers, and judges, who ought &amp; indeed can judge of hereſie onely by outward ſignes. Betweene a Miniſter and Poperie let there bee a great <hi>Chaſma,</hi> a diſtance as wide as betweene heaven, and earth, nay heaven and hell: yet if his phraſe do but ſmell of Poperie, if his words, though not his meaning, trench neere upon it, men will preſently exclaime that he hath a Pope in his belly, at leaſt that he ſounds for a <hi>Parley,</hi> &amp; thinks upon conditions of peace with the Romiſh harlot. And beſides, as this ſuſpicious complying in phraſe, and language with the knowne errours of Popelings, or other novellers and corrupt teachers grieves the ſetled and judicious, ſo farther it ſtaggers weaklings, confirmes and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3506:18"/>aliens, and apoſtates, rather opens than ſtops the mouths of gaine-ſaying carpers, and ſooner diſadvantageth the truth, than converts an adverſary. So farre is it from effecting the uſually pretended end, reconciliation; as that to uſe the ſimilitude of our Saviour, quis loquitur, ſuam, <hi>v.</hi> 16. like the putting of a new p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ece of cloth unto an old garment, it maketh the rent worſe, and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. There goeth a manuſcript from hand to hand, ſaid to bee penned by a learned D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> of this Church, wherein (that amidſt and notwithſtanding all the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of opinions there may be yet preſerved in the Church the unitie both of faith, and charity) private men are adviſed in their own writings to obſerve <hi>forma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſanorum verborum,</hi> and to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine not onely from ſuſpected opinions, but as much as may be alſo from phraſes and ſpeeches obnoxious to miſconſtruction, and exception.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:3506:18"/>
            <p>For firſt, it is not enough, much leſſe a thing to be gloried in, for a man to be able by ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of wit, to finde <hi>loop-holes,</hi> how to evade, &amp; by colourable pretences, to make that, which through heat of paſſion, or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of oppoſition hath falne from him <hi>unadviſedly,</hi> to ſeeme howſoever defenſible. But hee ſhould have a care to ſuffer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to paſſe from him whereat an ingenious, and diſpaſſionate adverſary (though diſſenting from him in opinion,) might yet have cauſe to take diſtaſt, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception.</p>
            <p>And beſides it were a thing of dangerous conſequence in the Church, if every man ſhould be ſuffered to publiſh freely whatſoever might by ſome ſtraine of wit be made capable of a good conſtruction, if of it ſelfe it ſounded ill or ſuſpiciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. For ſo many erroneous, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy notions implicitly and vertually ſerving to the patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3506:19"/>and protection of ſchiſme or hereſie, might be cunningly conveighed into the mindes of men, and impreſſions thereof inſenſibly wrought in their hearts, to the great dammage and diſtraction of the Church.</p>
            <p>This laſt reaſon for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance you may meete with in <hi>Aquinas</hi> 2.2 dae <hi>q.</hi> 11. <hi>a.</hi> 2. where (having told us out of <hi>Hierome, ex verbis inordinatè prolatis fit haereſis:</hi> that by unwary irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar expreſſions, by words diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly ſpoken, the moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous hereſies have often ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken their firſt riſe, &amp; originall,) he afterward gives us the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hereof: <hi>Similiter enim per verba quae quis loquitur, ſuam, fidem profitetur: eſt enim con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſio actus fidei: &amp; ideò ſi ſit inordinata locutio circa ea quae ſunt fidei ſequi poteſt ex hoc cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptio fidei: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde Leo Papa quâdam epiſtolâ ad Proterium Epiſcopum Alexandrinum, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, quòd inimici crucis Chriſti
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3506:19"/>omnibus &amp; verbis noſtris inſidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur et ſyllabis, ſi ullam illis vel tenue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occaſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> demus, quâ Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoriano ſenſuinos co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gruere men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiantur.</hi> Likewiſe a man profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his faith by words, which he ſpeaketh, for confeſſion is an outward act of faith, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if there be but an inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſpeech about matters of faith, the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of faith may hereupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enſue. Whence <hi>Leo</hi> the Pope in a certain epiſtle unto <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius</hi> biſhop of <hi>Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dria</hi> ſaith, that the enemies of Chriſts Croſſe lye in wait for all our <hi>words</hi> and <hi>ſyllables,</hi> if in them wee give any the leaſt occaſion upon which they may faine that wee comply with <hi>Neſtoria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme.</hi> Hence is it, that, <hi>Aquinas</hi> himſelfe having propoſed this queſtion, whether or no this propoſition be true, Chriſt is a creature, in his anſwer thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to tels us, firſt in generall, <hi>cum haereticis nec nomina debemus habere communia, ne corum er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rori
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3506:20"/>favere videamur,</hi> then more particularly, unto the queſtion that the Arrian heretickes have ſaid that Chriſt is a creature, and leſſe than the Father, in regard not only of the humane nature, but alſo divine perſon; and therefore reſolves, that leaſt we ſhould ſeeme to countenance their errour, we muſt not ſay ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, that Chriſt is a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and leſſe than his Father, but only with this limitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the humane nature.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ariani autem haeretici Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum dixerunt eſſe creaturam, &amp; minorem Patre, non ſolùm ratione humanae naturae, ſed eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ratione divinae perſonae, &amp; ideò non eſt abſolutè dicendum, quòd Chriſtus ſit creatura, vel minor Patre, ſed cum determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione, ſcilicet ſecundùm huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam naturam.</hi> Nay not only <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas,</hi> but generally all the Schoole-men, and Civilians too, are ſoe preciſe in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, as that among the degrees
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3506:20"/>of damnable propoſitions are ranked by them not onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions downerightly <hi>hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,</hi> or <hi>erroneous,</hi> but alſo
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Propoſitio ſcandaloſa qua etiam malè ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans, ſeu piarum aurium offenſiva, appellatur, quae praber occaſionem ruina au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor. bus, hoc eſt, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitatem cadend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in haereſim, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t ſunt multa propoſitiones, qualicet cum modificatione ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a, ſunt verae, per ſe tamen &amp; abſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lutè ſine modificatione prolata videntur favere propoſitionibus hareticalib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t ſi quis aſſereret ſimpliciter Patrem majorem Filio, &amp; Deum in incarnatione factum creaturam &amp; ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, qua magis ſunt exponenda, quam extendenda.</hi> Arnoldus Alb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tinus de agnoſcendis aſſertionibus Catholicis &amp; haeteticis, quaeſt. 60. <hi>Propoſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſin ſaptens, aut malè circaea, quae ad fidem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, ſonans, eſt illa quae in prima ſignificatione, quam verba prima fac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e oſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>endunt, ſenſum habet haereticum, quam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e intellecta ſenſum aliquem habet verum.</hi> Alphonſus à Caſtrode juſt a haeretico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum punitione: cap. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitio ſapiens haereſin, Propoſitio malè ſonans,</hi> every propoſition, that doth but ſmel, that hath but a ſmacke of hereſie, that ſounds but ill or ſuſpiciouſly; &amp; ſuch are all propoſitions, that in the firſt ſignification, which their words at firſt bluſh ſeeme to import, have an hereticall ſence; all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, that of themſelves, that is, uttered <hi>abſolutly</hi> without any <hi>explanation,</hi> or <hi>qualification,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:3506:21"/>ſeeme to favour or countenance hereticall propoſitions, although they be capable of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and with many <hi>cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous limitations,</hi> and <hi>reſtrictions</hi> might paſſe for currant. And therefore was it, that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Baſil</hi> condemned this propoſition, <hi>Chriſt ſinnes dayly,</hi> becauſe taken properly 'tis falſe, and againſt the faith, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though perhaps it may be freed from errour, if expounded in an unproper ſenſe, thus; Chriſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth dayly, not in himſelfe, but his <hi>members,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Expl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> turoptimè, modoſuprà tacto de propoſitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne aequivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, quae in proprio ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo ſenſu poteſt eſſe haretica, &amp; in alto ettam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priè Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica, nam illa abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutè, et ſine diſtinctione vel decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione prolaetame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ò dicitur malè ſonans, in quo diſtinctio alia adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beripoteſt. Nam quadam propoſitio dicitur ab extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeco malè ſonans, alia ab intrinſeco. Ab extrinſéco vocatur, quando ſuſpitio, vel maliu ſonu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> non expro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitione nude ſumpta, ſed cum circumſtantiis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonae, loci, aut temporis oritur.</hi> Suarez de triplic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Theologica tract. de F.de. Diſp. 19. Sect. 7. <hi>Dicendum igitur eſt, quòd propoſitio ſapiens haereſin illa eſt, qua quam vis no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> appareat hareſis manifeſta, quin potius aliquando poterit habere aliquem bonum ſenſum, tamen ex quibuſdam circumſtant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is, Vel ex parte aſſe entis, vel ex tempor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m calamitate ſaporem quendam habet hareſis, &amp; ſuſpic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>onis, judicio pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum &amp; ſapientum, id eſt, ſuſpicionem quandam ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorem vel minorem pro qualitate circumſtantiarum.</hi> Bannes.</note> Suarez</hi> ſaith,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3506:21"/>that if an equivocall propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on having two proper ſenſes, one <hi>Catholicke,</hi> another <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall</hi> bee delivered abſolutely without any <hi>diſtinction</hi> or <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration,</hi> in which ſenſe 'tis meant, it is then deſervedly ſaid to be <hi>propoſitio malè ſonans.</hi> The ſame author goeth on, and tells us, that a propoſition is ſaid to be <hi>malè ſonans</hi> not onely <hi>ab in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſeco,</hi> but alſo <hi>ab extrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co,</hi> when the ſuſpition or ill ſound thereof ariſeth not from the propoſition taken nakedly as it is in it ſelfe, but conſidered joyntly with the circumſtances either of the perſon delivering, of the time or place, in which it is delivered. Omitting his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, I will give you others more true, and ſavory. The word <hi>Sacrament</hi> with the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient founded no other, than an holy ſignificant rite: in thoſe times, than to have called Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie, Orders &amp;c. Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, had beene (it may be
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3506:22"/>without all manner of offence. But now, ſince the Church of Rome hath peremptorily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, that there be <hi>ſeaven Sacraments properly,</hi> and <hi>ſtrictly</hi> ſoe called, ſeaven outward and ſenſible ſignes, which by divine inſtitution have annexed unto them the promiſe of juſtifying grace. He that ſhall now terme any thing a Sacrament, beſides <hi>Baptiſme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> renders himſelfe thereby ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſuſpected.</p>
            <p>In the writings of the Fathers the words of Satisfaction, and Merit have beene of large uſe. Satisfaction ſignified every <hi>bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, afflictive acknowledgement,</hi> or <hi>penitentiall mortification</hi> of our ſinnes, whereby wee <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent,</hi> &amp; <hi>turne</hi> away Gods hand and puniſhments for them. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> denoted onely <hi>obtaining pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement, impetration,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this acception of the words, a man might ſafely have heretofore affirmed, that our
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3506:22"/>prayers, almes, and other good workes are <hi>ſatisfactorie</hi> and <hi>meritorious.</hi> But now ſince ſome of the Romaniſts have wreſted theſe ſayings of the Fathers unto a worſe ſenſe, than they were uttered in: and hereupon taught that workes are properly <hi>ſatisfactory,</hi> juſt <hi>compenſations</hi> for our ſinnes, wherein wee make recompence unto Gods wronged juſtice, and redeeme our ſelves at leaſt from <hi>temporall</hi> puniſhments; that workes are <hi>ſtrictly</hi> and <hi>properly meritorious</hi> of eternall life, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving and earning it <hi>ex c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digno,</hi> in the way of condigne wages; as if there were an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualitie of due proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene it and them, without all regard unto Gods gracious acceptance of them; hee that ſhall now averre theſe propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, may without breach of charitie be juſtly thought to embrace them in that falſe, and erroneous ſenſe, which our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3506:23"/>the Papiſts take them in.</p>
            <p>Hitherto concerning <hi>doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall appearance</hi> of evill in <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines. Practicall appearance</hi> of evill in <hi>manners,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr Solater in locum.</note> or matters of practice next followes; and that may againe be divided into <hi>Reall</hi> or <hi>Imaginary.</hi> The diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is the ſame with that of others, <hi>Aliquid habet speciom mali, vel per ſe ex conditione ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,
<note place="margin">Forbeſius lien c. pag. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8.</note> vel per accidens ex aliorum interpretatione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The difference between theſe muſt be well weighed, elſe we may as fowlely be miſtaken, as once the <hi>Pontickes</hi> were, who as <hi>Florus</hi> tels us, fighting in a night with the Romans, <hi>per er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorem longius cadentes umbras fuas quaſi hoſtium corpora pete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant:</hi> miſtaking their owne <hi>ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes</hi> projected long as at the going downe of the Moone, laid at them as at the very <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> of their enemies; or as the Romans themſelves, were, unto
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3506:23"/>whom when <hi>Tiberius Grac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> touched his head with his hand to exliort the people as by a ſigne to ſtand upon their guard for their lives, it ſeemed as if he demanded a diademe. <hi>Cùm plebem ad defenſionem ſalutis ſua manu caput tangens, horta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retur, praebuit ſpeciem regni ſibi, &amp; diadema poſcentis. Flor. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>To diſtinguiſh them then; a <hi>reall</hi> appearance of evill flowes <hi>per ſe ex natura operis,</hi> from the nature and condition of the fact it ſelfe; when that of it ſelfe, and in its owne nature is a very <hi>probable ſigne of evill,</hi> and ſo it is, although it be not <hi>intrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> ſinfull, when it is <hi>per ſe,</hi> an occaſion of ſinne in our ſelves, and of ſcandall unto others, it muſt bee <hi>occaſio data, non ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, when naturally, and not onely caſually it may prove, and ordinarily doth prove an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of an incentive to ſin in our ſelves.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:3506:24"/>
            <p>Secondly, when it becomes an occaſion of ſcandall or offence: of ſcandall tending unto <hi>ſinne</hi> in the <hi>weake,</hi> of ſcandall tending unto <hi>ſorrow</hi> and <hi>vexation</hi> in the <hi>ſtrong</hi> and <hi>diſcreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Talis ſc. materialis uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ſemper hab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem mali non ex ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidenti ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tùm, ſed quaſi per ſe, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſito Eccle ſiae ſtatu.</hi> Suar. de Legibus lib. 9. cap. 14.</note> Such an appearance of Juda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme, (than which few greater evils) is there in the Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of thoſe Aethiopian Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that live under <hi>Preſter John.</hi> Such was the appearance of evill in Chriſtians ſitting at meat in the Temples of Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Idols, in <hi>Naamans</hi> bowing himſelfe in the houſe of Rim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; however <hi>Cajetan</hi> excuſe him with a pretty diſtinction, <hi>inter genuflexionem imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vam, &amp; genuflexionem obſequii.</hi> And ſuch alſo is that appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of evill in a <hi>good mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate fellowſhip</hi> with <hi>bad ones,</hi> in a true and formall complian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie with aliens in the ſignes of profeſſion. As in a Proteſtants preſence at the ſuperſtitious, and <hi>Idolatrous</hi> worſhip of Papiſts,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3506:24"/>or in any other complementings with them in the expreſſion of that <hi>worſhip</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now no actions that have this <hi>reall appearance</hi> of <hi>evill,</hi> are upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any pretext whatſoever to be ventured upon, becauſe in them there is alwaies a ſcandall gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, an <hi>active ſcandall,</hi> as is plaine from <hi>Aquinas</hi> his defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of ſcandall, 2. 2dae. qu. 43. art. 1. <hi>Scandalum</hi> (ſaith hee) underſtand it of an <hi>active Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall</hi>) <hi>eſt dictum vel ſactum mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nùs rectum, praebens alter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem ruinae.</hi> For firſt, a fact is <hi>minus rectum,</hi> ſome way, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther irregular, not onely when it is a ſin, but alſo when it hath a manifeſt ſhew of ſinne: and ſecondly the bare, and naked ſhew of ſin may <hi>praebere alteri occaſionem ruinae; morally</hi> lead another to ſinne, as well as ſinne it ſelfe. For this I could muſter up the <hi>ſuffrages</hi> of all the Schoolemen, a generation of divines that are none of the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3506:25"/>preciſeſt, either in poſitions or practice. But I will not trouble my reader with the teſtimonies of above two of them. <hi>Opus malum</hi> (ſaith <hi>Suarez</hi>) <hi>vel ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bens ſpeciem mali, quod de ſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductivum est ad peccandum, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandum eſt, nam illud eſt verè ſcandalum activum, ut patet ex definitione ejus, moraliter enim inducit hominem ad malum. Quod verò non oporteat eſſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rè malum, ſed ſatis ſit apparere, patet,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ. c.</hi> 5.22. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>Ratio eſt, quia tenemur rectè operari, non ſolùm coram Deo, ſed etiam coram hominibus. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundò, quia cum opus habet spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem mali, inducitur proximus ad malum opus, non ſolum ſuâ malitiâ ſed etiam ex vi mei ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, &amp; ex quadam fragilitate. Suarez, op. de triplici virtute tract.</hi> 2. <hi>diſp.</hi> 10. <hi>ſect.</hi> 3. <hi>Quotieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque datur occaſio ſcandali</hi> (ſaith <hi>Vaſquez</hi>) <hi>malo opere, aut habente speciem mali, ſemper im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putatur ſcandalum tribuenti oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionem,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3506:25"/>five ſcandalum ſequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ex malitia, five infirmitate, aut ignorantiâ. Tunc enim qui praebet occaſionem ſcandali, pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat peccata ſcandali activi: quod nullâratione licet. Ratio verò eſt quia nullâ juſtâ aut rationa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili cauſâ excuſari poteſt aliquis à peccato, qui coram alio peccat, vel exercet opus habens speciem mali; &amp; ideò jure optimo dicitur tribuere occaſionem peccandi, quia tale opus ex ſe occaſio eſt peccandi. Vaſquez opuſculis Moralibus, tract. de Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That appearance of evill in an action which is but <hi>imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> is onely aſcribed thereunto by <hi>extrinſecall denomination,</hi> from our owne or others <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceits</hi> and <hi>cenſures</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon.</p>
            <p>Firſt, from <hi>our owne.</hi> And here, if a man be in his owne conſcience ſtedfaſtly, fully, and firmely perſwaded that ſuch an
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3506:26"/>action is evill and unlawfull, which yet in truth is not ſo,
<note place="margin">See Dr Sanderſon on Rom. 14.23.</note> but lawfull: what ought hee to doe?</p>
            <p>Why, wee muſt take into our conſideration the <hi>nature</hi> of the <hi>action,</hi> and the <hi>condition</hi> of the perſon, that harbours this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſwaſion of the action.</p>
            <p>If the action in its nature bee not <hi>neceſſary,</hi> but <hi>indifferent,</hi> and <hi>arbitrary,</hi> and the perſon miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judging it, be in reſpect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>ſui juris,</hi> not determined therein by the command of any <hi>ſuperiour power.</hi> Why then he is bound in conſcience during this his opinion, to abſtaine from the action. For wee ſuppoſe it indifferent, and a man may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully forbeare action where there is no neceſſitie of doing. Wee ſuppoſe it, although indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, yet againſt Conſcience: and whatſoever is done <hi>repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nante conſcientiâ,</hi> with a ſettled <hi>reluctancie</hi> of a mans owne judgement, and conſcience a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3506:26"/>it, cannot be of faith, and <hi>whatſoever is not of faith is ſinne. Rom.</hi> 14.24. That is, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver action is done with a firme perſwaſion of the lawfulneſſe thereof, let it be <hi>quoad rem,</hi> and <hi>eſſentially,</hi> in it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſelfe lawfull, nay neceſſary, yet it becomes <hi>quoad hominem,</hi> and <hi>accidentally</hi> evill, unto him it is ſinne. Now that action may lawfully, muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be forborne, that can be omitted, but cannot be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted without ſinne.</p>
            <p>But now on the contrary, if either the action be in its <hi>nature neceſſary,</hi> or the perſon entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this miſpriſion thereof be injoyned performance of it by ſome <hi>ſuperiour power,</hi> that can lawfully challenge obedience from him, and ſo the action too, (though indifferent) for its <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> be yet in its <hi>uſe,</hi> and unto him become <hi>neceſſary.</hi> Why then this miſperſwaſion of its unlawfulneſſe cannot bind to abſtaine from it, for ſo it ſhould
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3506:27"/>oblige unto either omiſſion of a neceſſary dutie, or elſe diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto lawfull autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, both great ſinnes. And <hi>nulla eſt obligatio ad illicita.</hi> There is no obligation unto things unlawfull can lye upon us.</p>
            <p>But yet although this errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conceit of the unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this action, ſuppoſed to be neceſſary either in its nature, or at leaſt in its uſe, becauſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by authority, doth not <hi>obligaere,</hi> that is, ſo bind, as that I muſt follow it, yet it doth <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gare,</hi> ſo <hi>intangle</hi> and <hi>perplexe,</hi> as that I cannot without ſinne oppoſe it, becauſe whoſoever goeth againſt his Conſcience, (whether ill or well informed it matters not) goes againſt the <hi>will</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> although not for the <hi>thing</hi> he doth, yet for the <hi>manner</hi> of doing it, although not <hi>materially,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ameſ. de Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia. l. 1, c. 4.</note> yet <hi>formally,</hi> and <hi>interpretatively,</hi> becauſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Conſcience dictates
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3506:27"/>a man takes for the will of God, each mans conſcience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Deputy God</hi> to informe &amp; direct him. Looke as, hee who reviles, wounds, kills a private man, miſtaking him for the King, is guilty of high treaſon againſt the King himſelfe: ſoe, he that thwarts the judgement of even an erroneous conſcience, fights againſt God, warres againſt heaven, becauſe what his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſayes, hee thinkes to be the voyce of heaven.</p>
            <p>The only way then for a man to reſcue himſelfe out of theſe difficulties is to <hi>rectifie</hi> his <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience;</hi> to depoſe &amp; correct the error thereof, ſo he ſhall eſcape contempt of the judgement of his owne conſcience on the one hand, &amp; breach of either Gods or mans lawes on the other.</p>
            <p>An <hi>imaginary appearance of evill</hi> iſſues, ſecondly, from the ſuppoſalls of, not onely our ſelves, but others that cenſure it, whoſe judgments are either
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3506:28"/>
               <hi>miſled</hi> by <hi>ignorance</hi> and <hi>weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> or elſe <hi>blinded</hi> through <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>prejudice,</hi> ſuch was that in the moving of <hi>Hannah's</hi> lips, not afforded by her <hi>fact,</hi> but onely faſtned on it by old <hi>Eli</hi> his <hi>haſty cenſoriouſneſſe,</hi> nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther appearance of evill was there in our Saviours healing the diſeaſed, his Diſciples pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and eating of the eares of corne on the Sabbaoth Day, 'twas not grounded on their <hi>actions,</hi> but onely fancied by the <hi>Phariſees ſwelling</hi> uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what other is that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of evill with which ſome unjuſtly charge our cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies? 'tis onely conceived by their uncharitable pręjudice, not really given by them.</p>
            <p>This <hi>imaginary appearance</hi> of evill proceeds from either ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſalls of <hi>proud,</hi> or <hi>weake ones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The cenſures or ſuppoſals of <hi>proud ones</hi> we may ſleight, our warrant is our Sauiours Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, when his Diſciples told
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3506:28"/>him, that the Phariſees tooke offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at his ſpeech, he made no reckoning therof, but anſwered,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scandala Phariſaeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum pror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenda, na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qui non ex ignor ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> aut infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitaete, ſed ex malitia ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zatur: Non laborat ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li altquà neceſsitate ſpirituali, cui non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit ipſe ſine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pe alteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> proximi facile proſpirere, mut andoprauam ſuam voluntatem: erg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> alter non tenetur, tunccum aliquo ſuo detrimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to proſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icere</hi> Gregor. de Valentia. <hi>Quoties ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalum paſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vum alterius futurum eſt, ex m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>litia nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> debet omit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere opus, quod nec eſt malum, nec habe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſpeciem malipropter malitiam alterius, quando opus illud utile eſt temporaliter, vel ſpiritualiter ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, quia non poſtulat ratio, ut malitia alterius cum dam no noſtro ſuccurramus, alias quilibet malitia ſua poſſit nobis nocere, ut omitteremus opus nobis utile: malitia autem alterius nobis nocerenon debet.</hi> Luiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius Tunianus.</note> let them alone. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.13.14. and we warranted by his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, may then be ſecure and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſſe of many calumnies &amp; groundleſſe exceptions againſt the government, diſcipline, and ceremonies of our Church: for there hath beene ſo much ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken &amp; written concerning theſe ſubjects, as that the pretence of weakneſſe may ſeeme to bee taken; away from thoſe that are capable of information.</p>
            <p>But what if this <hi>imaginary</hi> appearance of evill flow from
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3506:29"/>the ſuppoſall of a <hi>weake one,</hi> yet an <hi>holy one.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why then it muſt be omitted, but with this caution, ſo it may be without <hi>ſinne,</hi> or as the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary gloſſe upon that 15. of <hi>Mathew v.</hi> 12.13.14 reſolves it, <hi>Salvatriplici veritate vitae, juſtitiae, doctrinae,</hi> ſo the three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold verity of <hi>life, juſtice,</hi> and <hi>doctrine</hi> be preſerved ſafe: <hi>Nam per hanc triplicem veritatem</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gregory de Valentia</hi>) <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligitur omnis rectitudo &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitas à peccato in actionibus humanis. Veritas namque vit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> continetur in actionibus rectis, quas quis in ſeipſo excrcet conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nienter rectae rationi &amp; appeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui recto atque adeò verè verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te quadam practicâ: Veritas au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem juſtitiae rectis actionibus quae exercentur erga alterum ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, convenienter rectae rationi, prout verè &amp; abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> peccato opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet: veritas denique doctrinae continetur fide verâ, &amp; minimè erroneâ:</hi> By this triple verity
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3506:29"/>is underſtood all the rectitude and freedome from ſinne, that is in humaneactions, for the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of life is contained in thoſe regular actions; which any one exerciſeth in. and towards him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe agreeable to right reaſon, &amp; a well governed appetite, &amp;c. The veritie of juſtice conſiſts in thoſe regular actions, which are performed toward another, likewiſe ſutably to right reaſon, as it behoveth, truly, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne.</p>
            <p>And to conclude, the veritie of doſtrine conſiſts in a true, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, and unerring faith: if theſe three verities be kept inviolate, every thing muſt bee abſtained from, upon which followes <hi>ſcandalum puſillorum,</hi> a ſcandall ſpringing from either the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; or weakneſſe of our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but becauſe this reſolution may be thought both too gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and obſcure the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men themſelves, ſumbling much about its explication, wee will
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3506:30"/>therefore goe to worke more diſtinctly and particularly.</p>
            <p>Conſider whether or no the action, in which this appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of evill is imagined to be, is <hi>neceſſary,</hi> or <hi>indifferent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be <hi>neceſſary,</hi> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded by God, it muſt not be omitted though all the world ſhould be offended: For evill muſt not bee done that good may come ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>Cal. l. 3. Inſt. c. 19. Sect. 13.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Scandalu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod oritur ex rebus per ſe bonis, &amp; neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis, non li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet evitare; qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a non eſt facien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ut eveniat bonum Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num enim eſt expete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dum, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt; non ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitur au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem quate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s bonum eſt, ſi malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſimul expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur. Nam qui expetit bonum, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> à malo: qui aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abhorret à malo, qua malu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, is nullo malo quodc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſit non poteſt allics. Jam verò nulla ſunt resplanè neceſſariae pratereas qua ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in ſe bonae, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ejuſmodi, ut niſi volunt as illas expe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>at, à ſuo vero, &amp; proprio objecto abhorret: it aq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ut maxime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tumul tuetur mund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, tamen omnia, etiam ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rem a quaeque ſubeunda ſunt, ut ſie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> illsbata De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> gloria.</hi> Cameron in electiora quaeda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> N Teſt.loca, Tom. 2. in Mat. 18.7.</p>
               </note>; <hi>Calvin</hi> telling us, regard ought to be had of charity limits, how farre, <hi>uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad aras,</hi> that is, ſo for our brothers ſake we offend not God: I may adde, ſo for our brothers ſake wee endanger not our owne ſoules. To prevent ſcandall and ſin in our brethren, wee may not runne upon ſinne our ſelves: for a well ordered Charitie, as <hi>Aquinas</hi> gives the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, 2, 2<hi>ae.</hi> q. 43 a. 7. beginneth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3506:30"/>ever at home, making a man chiefly deſire and endeavour the ſalvation of his owne ſoule, and conſequently more ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous to avoid ſinne in himſelfe, than to prevent it in other: I may not then omit or neglect neceſſary duties, becauſe to ſome they ſeeme but needleſſe niceties, I muſt not flie true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the <hi>power of godlineſſe,</hi> becauſe unto the world it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares but <hi>braineſicke peeviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and <hi>an irrationall preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> others errour may not be ſeconded, and countenanced with mine impiety, and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>Of this matter none ſpeake ſo fully, and clearly as the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in 2 <hi>dam,</hi> 2 <hi>da,</hi> q. 43. a. 7. where <hi>Thomas</hi> and all his inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters debate this queſtion. <hi>An bona ſpiritualia ſint propter ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalum dimittenda.</hi> Not to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion their rotten diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene matters of <hi>Councell,</hi> and matters of <hi>precept,</hi> we will only
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3506:31"/>out of them take notice, that there is a difference betweene <hi>tranſgreſſion</hi> of a <hi>precept,</hi> and a <hi>temporary, partiall,</hi> or <hi>occaſionall forbearance</hi> of the matter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by a precept.</p>
            <p>No precept whatſoever, whether of the law of <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> or elſe but <hi>poſitive,</hi> is for eſchewing the ſcandall of any whether weake or malicious, to be truly <hi>broken</hi> and <hi>tranſgreſſed.</hi> And a precept is tranſgreſſed whenſoever what is enjoyned in it is omitted at ſuch a time, and in ſuch a caſe, when all the particular circumſtances which we ought to regard being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered wee are tyed to perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Opera di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> prae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cepti affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mativi, qd non pro ſemper ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligat, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferri pro aliquo tempore quando cauſarent puſillis ſcandalum, don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> illi ſint meliùs inſtructi, ſed circumſtantia illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſcandaliſint mutatae, ita ut contingat praeceptum affirmativum etiam juris <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uaſi naturalis, aliquando hic, &amp; nunc non obligare propter concurſum nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivi praecepti de non ponendo offendiculo puſillis.</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes Wiggers.</note> But yet however upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergencie of ſcandall, that
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3506:31"/>which is commanded by ſome precepts may <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc,</hi> in ſome times<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and at ſome places, be omitted, may for a while be forborne, untill the ſcandall taken thereby can bee removed by information, or inſtruction, or untill the circumſtances of the ſcandall be ſome way or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther changed. Promulgation of a truth, and Chriſtian reproofe are duties commanded by God, and yet are to be ſometimes ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained from, for ſcandalls ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by not onely the weake, but alſo malicious. <hi>Reproue not a ſcorner leſt hee hate thee. Prov.</hi> 9.8. <hi>Speake not in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ares of a foole for he will deſpiſe the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of thy words. Prov.</hi> 23.9. <hi>Give not that which is holy unto the dogges, neither caſt yee your pearles before ſwine, leſt they trample them under their feete,</hi> and turne againe, <hi>and rent you, Mat.</hi> 7.6.</p>
            <p>To explaine this farther, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe muſt bee had unto that
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3506:32"/>old and golden rule, <hi>Affirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va praecepta ſemper obligant, non ad ſemper.</hi> Affirmative precepts doe alwaies bind, but not to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies: ſo that wee are not bound to perform alwaies what they enjoyne, but onely <hi>loco &amp; tempore debitis,</hi> when wee have due time and place. Now as by the <hi>intercurrencie</hi> of other <hi>cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances,</hi> ſo eſpecially by <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence</hi> of the <hi>ſcandall</hi> of weake brethren, there may not be opportunity and ſeaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of doing what wee are ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged unto by ſome affirmative precepts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo thoſe precepts may <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc</hi> ceaſe to be obligatory: For when the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of two precepts ſeeme to meete together at the very ſame time, that which is of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter obligation tieth us, and ſoe conſequently wee are for the preſent freed from the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the other. Now the <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative precept</hi> of eſchewing the ſcandall of the weake is more
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3506:32"/>
               <hi>obligatory,</hi> than many affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive precepts, and therefore to uſe the words of <hi>Malderus, Contingit aliquando praeceptum naturale affirmativum, hic &amp; nunc non obligare, propter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſum negativi praecepti natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralis de vitando ſcandalo puſillo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum:</hi> For example, vindicative juſtice binds a Magiſtrate to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute wrath upon him that doth evill; Charity on the other ſide obligeth him to hinder as much as hee can the ſcandall of the weake; now Charity is a vertue, of an higher note and nature than vindicative juſtice: the precept belonging unto charity, [hinder as much as you can the ſcandall of the weake], doth more ſtrictly tye us, than that appertaining unto vindicative juſtice, [puniſh the guilty.] And therefore, if it be probable that a great and ſpreading ſcandall will be taken at the puniſhing of delinquents: a Magiſtrate may not tranſgreſſe againſt ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3506:33"/>and yet deferre the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof.</p>
            <p>But ſo manifold &amp; different are the degrees of obligation in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative precepts: ſuch is the varietie of circumſtances apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining unto the matters com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by thoſe precepts, and inconſtancy of alterations about thoſe circumſtances, as that I do not ſee how any unvariable rules, or conſtant directions can be given for Chriſtian carriage in this caſe. For particulars then, every man is to be left unto the guidance of his <hi>ſpirituall pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> and <hi>wiſedome,</hi> which is to direct him in a right apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and diſcretion of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; to define the oportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ſeaſonableneſſe of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing what is commanded by affirmative precepts: and to compare them, and the precept of eſchewing the ſcandall of the weake together, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to determine which is <hi>Hic &amp; Nunc</hi> moſt <hi>obligatory,</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:3506:33"/>or doth moſt ſtrictly tye us to the obedience of it, as being of greater moment. Onely in the generall wee may ſafely ſay thus much; that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as wee have ſaid, that for ſhunning the ſcandall of the weake, wee may forbeare the practice of things commanded by affirmative precepts, <hi>Hic &amp; Nunc,</hi> in ſome places, and at ſome times, it muſt alwaies be taken with this proviſo, that there be not incurred a <hi>greater</hi> and more <hi>perilous ſcandall,</hi> by <hi>forbearance,</hi> than would proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be <hi>occaſioned</hi> by <hi>practiſe</hi> of <hi>the thing commanded,</hi> which is done, when either firſt, <hi>more</hi> are <hi>ſcandalized</hi> by the <hi>forbearance,</hi> than in all likelihood would be at the <hi>practice:</hi> or elſe ſecondly, when the <hi>body,</hi> in generall, the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common wealth,</hi> or the greateſt and chiefeſt part of either is <hi>juſtly ſcandalized</hi> at the forbearance, and onely ſome few <hi>particular private perſons
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3506:34"/>ſtumble</hi> at the <hi>practice:</hi> or elſe thirdly, when others take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by this <hi>partiall</hi> and <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarie</hi> forbearance of what is commanded by <hi>affirmative pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts,</hi> to contemne the <hi>precepts themſelves,</hi> as being by this our carriage induced to believe, that we verily <hi>despiſe them,</hi> and do not ſo much, <hi>for a while for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare,</hi> as utterly <hi>diſclaime</hi> the practice of what they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
            <p>But now, if the action, in which this appearance of evill is ſuppoſed to be, be but <hi>indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent,</hi> then theſe two following things muſt be pondered. Firſt, whether, or no it be <hi>annexed</hi> with a <hi>neceſſary duty,</hi> or not. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, whether or no it bee <hi>undetermined,</hi> left to our owne <hi>libertie,</hi> and <hi>choice,</hi> or elſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by authority either <hi>Oeconomicall, Politicall,</hi> or <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be annexed to a neceſſary duty, we muſt not omit this, to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3506:34"/>abſtaine from that. So to flie the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of ſinne, wee ſhould embrace the <hi>body</hi> of ſinne, a ſin <hi>really,</hi> ſo a ſinne of <hi>omiſſion;</hi> for what is not good, if to omit a duty be not bad? Good muſt not be left undone, though evill <hi>per accidens</hi> come from it; much more, when only an appearance of evill is joyned to it. We muſt not then ſhun the Lords Table, becauſe ſome weaker judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments have imagined in the act of kneeling, a ſhew of idolatry. So to avoid but an <hi>imaginary appearance</hi> of evill unto <hi>men,</hi> we ſhall <hi>appeare indeed</hi> unto <hi>God</hi> to be <hi>evill.</hi> A Miniſter muſt not neglect the diſcharge of his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, becauſe ſome have ſuppoſed a ſhew of ſuperſtition in ſome harmeleſſe <hi>ceremonies</hi> annexed to its performance. So, to avoid mens unjuſt <hi>cenſures,</hi> he ſhould incurre a <hi>juſt woe and curſe</hi> from God: <hi>Woe be to me</hi> (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>if I preach not the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we are not, ſecondly, <hi>noſtri
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3506:35"/>juris;</hi> but reſtrained, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by authority, wee muſt not diſobey that, to <hi>ſatisfie</hi> a <hi>Brother; tranſgreſſe duty,</hi> to <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Charity:</hi> So to <hi>pleaſe men,</hi> we ſhould <hi>diſpleaſe God.</hi> So we ſhould do evil, that good might come thereof. When the obli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gation of two preceps ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lyeth upon us at the ſame time, and impoſſible for both to bee at once obeyed, in ſuch a caſe, becauſe there is no claſhing betweene Gods precepts, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth God by them impoſe upon his creatures any neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſinning, therefore one of theſe precepts muſt give place unto the other; to wit, that which enjoyneth a <hi>leſſe</hi> duty, unto that which preſcribes a more <hi>weightie,</hi> and <hi>preſſing one.</hi> Now the duties of juſtice (as a learned Inconformitant, even <hi>Ameſius</hi> himſelfe, <hi>Med. Theol. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. §. 62, 63. will tell us) are of ſtricter obligation, than thoſe of charity. Wee are
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3506:35"/>more bound to pay our debts, than to diſtribute almes. Hee that hath treſpaſſed againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is more ſtrictly tyed to ſue for reconciliation, than the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty who hath received the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Now to hinder the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall of the weake is a duty of charity, to obey the lawfull co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands of authority a dutie of juſtice, &amp; therefore of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter obligation, and moment. Unto it then the other muſt give place. I would have tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled farther in this argument, but that I am anticipated by the learned, and reverend Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours of Aberdene in their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies to the ſecond anſwers of the Covenanting Miniſters, who from page 65. unto 75. have purpoſely diſcuſſed this very queſtion, whether the precept of obedience to ſuperiours, or the precept of eſchewing ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall be more obligatory, and have there proved by many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable arguments, that the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3506:36"/>former precept, that of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to ſuperiours is of the twaine more obligatory. Thoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that deſire larger ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> concerning this matter, I ſhall referre unto the peruſall of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. However in the meane while let it not bee thought trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, if I inſert, what I judge in them, if not moſt, yet very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable. 'Tis this, <hi>Debitum obedientiae,</hi> the <hi>debt</hi> of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which we owe unto ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, is (ſay they, page 74.) not onely <hi>debitum morale,</hi> a <hi>debt</hi> or <hi>duty,</hi> unto which wee are tyed by <hi>morall honeſty,</hi> and Gods commandement, but alſo <hi>debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum legale,</hi> or <hi>debitum juſtitiae, (quod viz: fundatur in proprio jure alterius)</hi> a debt grounded upon the true, and proper right which our Superiours have to exact this dutie of us; ſo that they may accuſe us of injury, and cenſure us, if wee performe it not. There is a great difference betwixt theſe two ſorts of debts
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3506:36"/>and the laſt is farre more obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie than the firſt: as for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: A man oweth money to the poore by a <hi>morall debt,</hi> but to his creditour he oweth them by <hi>legall debt,</hi> or debt <hi>of juſtice;</hi> and therefore he is more ſtrictly obliged to pay his creditour, than to give almes. So by morall honeſty, and Gods precept alſo, a man oweth to his neighbour a pious carefulneſſe to hinder ſinne in him, by admonition, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, good example, and by omiſſion, even of things law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, when hee foreſeeth that his neighbour, in reſpect of his weakeneſſe, will be ſcandalized by them. But his neighbour hath not ſuch a right to exact theſe things of him, neither can hee have action againſt him for not performing of them, as our law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſuperiours have, for our due obedience. Thus they.</p>
            <p>Hence then may we ſhape an anſwer unto that ſame frequent clamour of ſome tumultuous
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3506:37"/>ſpirits, that our conformity for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, is wondrous offenſive to many of our weake brethren.</p>
            <p>Firſt ſuppoſe it be ſo, better they without thy fault bee of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, <hi>ſcandalized at thee,</hi> than that the Magiſtrate be with thy fault <hi>diſobeyed by thee.</hi> It is no ſafe courſe to provide for the peace of thy brothers conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, by wounding thine owne with the ſinne of diſobedience againſt authority, to which for conſcience ſake thou art to yeeld ſubjection: wee muſt not to comply with mens humours reſiſt the Ordinance of God, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the voice of the Church, rather than a weake brother ſhould be offended, ſcandalized, wee may, and ſometimes muſt part with our owne right: but we ought not to rob the Church of hers by bereaving her of her power, by denying her our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Nay farther, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that rather than a weake brother ſhould be ſcandalized,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3506:37"/>wee may <hi>pro Hic &amp; Nunc,</hi> in ſome particular times &amp; places, pretermit what ſuperiours pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, provided they take no diſtaſt thereat, and others by our example bee not encouraged to contemne their perſons, callings, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mands; for ſo a greater, &amp; more pernicious ſcandall will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr'd, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was declin'd. But we are not upon occurrence of any ſcandall whatſoever, taken by whomſoever, either abſolutely to deny, and utterly refuſe obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the lawfull in juncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our publike governours, whether temporall or eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall; or ſo much as contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly and ſcandalouſly for a while omit the practice of what they injoyne. And omiſſion of what they require, is than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous, when they peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily urge the practice of it, than ſcandalous when it hartens others to a contempt of their authority. To grant any of theſe lawfull, what were it? alaſſe!
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3506:38"/>but to licenſe confuſion both in Church, and common-wealth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I demand whether or no, the offence given to, or taken by a Magiſtrate, who is a brother, and withall a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, be not greater than that which is given to or taken by one, who is onely a brother? An impartiall judge will ſoone de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, that the <hi>double relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>brother</hi> and <hi>magiſtrate,</hi> weigheth downe the ſingle and naked relation of a brother. Howſoever I am ſure, that the whole exceeds the parts ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally conſidered: the <hi>relation</hi> of <hi>mother</hi> exacts more at our hands than that of brother, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in warding a blow from my <hi>brother,</hi> I am to take care, that thereby the ſame ſtroake light not upon the <hi>head of my mother</hi> the <hi>Church.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, as <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts to give none offence, neither to Jew, nor Gentile, ſo he addes in a farther ſpecialtie, <hi>more</hi> to the <hi>Church</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:3506:38"/>of <hi>God,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.37.
<note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhop Morton.</note> The Jewes and Gentiles were but parts, the Church of God the whole, they but brethren, ſhee the mother.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Si nefas ſit vel pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſillum qué piam Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalizare, &amp; praeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terit alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gata colla mola aſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria demergi quempiam in profun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, quam ſcandal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zare unum ex puſillis Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s: quam eſt horren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum flagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium, &amp; quam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troci ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicandum ſcandalizare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>os, quorum un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffenſio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>agis per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>culo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a, quam al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orum mul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rum, &amp;c.</hi> Forbeſius Irenic. pag. 40<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> If then it were better to bee throwne into the bottome of the ſea, with a mill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone about ones necke, than to offend a little one, a poore and illiterate artizan, what expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall wee then finde anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the haynouſneſſe of a ſcandall, given to a pious ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, to a religious Prince, to a Parliament, and Convocation, to a whole Church, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth?</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe the action indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, not annexed to a neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry duty, wee alſo left to the uſe of our libertie, what then?</p>
            <p>Two things are here eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to be conſidered. 1. The <hi>quality</hi> of the <hi>actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> excepted at.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:3506:39"/>2. The <hi>difference</hi> of <hi>times and places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To beginne with the firſt. The action ſo quarell'd at by thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is either of <hi>none,</hi> or <hi>great</hi> importance to thee.</p>
            <p>If it be none importance, as affording thee either none, or but ſmall pleaſure and profit, offend not thy brother by an unſeaſonable exerciſe of thy li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. Know, that as authoritie, ſo charity ſhould alſo reſtraine it, conſider that by this undue uſe of thy libertie thou ſinneſt againſt thy brother, and by ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt him thou ſinneſt againſt Chriſt, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12.</p>
            <p>But now, if it be of <hi>ſome weight</hi> and <hi>moment,</hi> as yeelding thee ſome great profit and pleaſure, why thou muſt a while forbeare it, untill thy brother may bee better inform'd; and to informe him that the action is lawfull which offends him, thou muſt take care too; otherwiſe thou wilt prejudice the truth
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3506:39"/>through thy regardleſſe ſilence, as alſo continue his weakneſſe, and foment in him a negative ſuperſtition. <hi>Let every one of us,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.2. <hi>pleaſe his neighbour for his good unto edification,</hi> And for a man to humour his neighbour in an erroneous and ſuperſtitious opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, however it may pleaſe him, yet not for his <hi>good</hi> unto <hi>aedification.</hi> Upon which ground I take it that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> as hee refuſ'd maintenance at Corinth, to avoid appearance of a <hi>covetous intention,</hi> and <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary affection</hi> in <hi>preaching;</hi> ſo alſo his juſt title and unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable right thereunto hee at large both profeſſeth, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth. But now if thy brother refuſe and contemne informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>Tunc deſinit eſſe ſcandalum puſilli ex infirmitate, aut ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plici ignorantia, &amp; incipit eſſe ſcandalum. Phariſaei ex pura malitia, aut ignorantia affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, &amp; craſſa.</hi> The ſhelter of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:3506:40"/>weakeneſſe is thereby taken from him, his judgement being now overſhadowed no longer with a meere weakeneſſe ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing out of ſimple ignorance, but with a proud &amp; wayward, if not envious, &amp; malitious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſſe, that is accompanied with a groſſe, wilfull, and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ignorance. He is no longer then to be accounted a weake one, but a proud and wilfull one, and for his peeviſhneſſe thou maiſt chooſe whether thou wilt forgoe thy liberty. However yet information doth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes alter the nature of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall. For the ſcandall of the weake, as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur articu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo</hi> 7. <hi>de ſcandalo puſillorum, ſi autem poſt reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem hujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalum du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, jam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur ex mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tia eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe; adverto quod au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor non aſsertivo verbo uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ſed opinativo, dic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndo, jam videtur ex malitia eſſe. poteſt ſiquidem cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ngere, quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> non ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces rationis redd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ta, vel propter pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtinam conſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem, qua facit apparere diſſonum, quod veritati conſonat, vel propter rationem apud cos magis app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentem, vel aliqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſmodi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; tunc quia mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tia non facit ſcandalum, ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gnorantia, vel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nfirm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, quam vis reddita ſit ratio, ceſſandum eſt ab hujuſmodi ſpir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tualibus non neceſſariis.</hi> Cajetan. in 2.2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.43. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Cajetan,</hi> and after him <hi>Petrus de Lorica</hi> obſerves,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:3506:40"/>may ſometimes laſt, <hi>Postquam reddita eſt ratio facti,</hi> after a reaſon of the fact, whereat they are ſcandalized, is rendred to them. For by reaſon of their extreame ignorance and ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of underſtanding, they may bee utterly incapable of information and inſtruction, or elſe ſome opinion, or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice whereunto they have beene long accuſtomed may caſt ſuch a miſt before their weake judgements, as that they may not be able preſently to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the reaſon that is given of the action, at which they ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And we ſhould ſo farre pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie the ſimplicitie of ſuch poore ſoules, as to abſtaine from that which ſcandalizeth them, if by ſuch abſtinence there accrew not to us any great loſſe, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenience. <hi>Petrus de Lori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> doth roundly, and fully ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe this matter. <hi>Veru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>quod Cajetanus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertit, ſcandalum puſillorum
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3506:41"/>perſeverare poſſe adhuc, poſt quam reddita eſt ratio facti, vel quia rationem non capiunt ob mentis tarditatem, vel ob conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem diu firmatam: in quo caſu docet Cajetanus omittendam eſſe actionem, ex qua ſcandalum ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiunt; vel differendam, donec ad ſaniorem mentem venerint. Quod ſolùm verum, ſi actio o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitti poteſt ſine jactura noſtrae utilitatis. Si enim magna uti. tilitas temporalis vel ſpiritualis interveniat, contemni poteſt ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalum puſillorum, poſt quam ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficienter admoniti ſint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will but recite a limitation of <hi>Gregory de Valentia,</hi> that comes under this head, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed. Having laid downe a rule, that for avoiding the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall of our neighbour, which ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ingeth either from his igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or weakneſſe, it behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth us, by the obligation of Charitie, to doe or omit that which may be done, or left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done without ſinne. hee after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:3506:41"/>puts this exception. <hi>Eſt autem animadvertendum han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> regulam intelligi debere de omni <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o, quod ſine peccato fieri, aut o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitti poſſit, non quomodo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unque, ſed moraliter, attentâ ſuavitate, quae eſt in jugo legum, divina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum: id eſt, quod ſine pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cato fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri aut omitti poſſit, ſine maxima etiam aliqua, &amp; penè intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili difficultate, ſpectatâ quoque in hac conditione perſonae, &amp;c.</hi> And indeed (mee thinkes) hee ſpeakes reaſonably. For im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable ſeemes it, that the ſweete moderation which is in the yoake of divine laws, ſhould conſiſt with ſo great a rigour, as in all matters whatſoever, not ſimply unlawfull to exact, not only a brotherly, but alſo a fervile compliancy with every ſuppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d weake one, whoſe weakeneſſe may be but pretended by thoſe that are willing to ſpeak favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For the humouring &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenting of every ſuppoſed weakling in all matters at which
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:3506:42"/>he takes offence, I conceive not my ſelfe bound to endanger my life, to hazard my eſtate, and fortunes, or to incurre any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther great, or notable inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience: for that would truely be <hi>durus ſermo,</hi> an hard ſaying; who are able to beare it?</p>
            <p>Secondly, we muſt put a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betweene times, and places; for however they bee but circumſtances of actions, and therefore extrinſecall to them, ſo that they cannot cauſe any ſuch eſſentiall variation in them, as to make thoſe acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons materially good, or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, which are of themſelves, in their owne nature indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; yet notwithſtanding the publicke, and ordinary abuſe of an action at ſuch a time, or in ſuch a place, may make it then and there, in that place and for that time appeare to be evill; although the ſame action at another time, and in the ſame place, or in another
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:3506:42"/>place at the ſame time, may not be obnoxious to any ſuch cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, <hi>time</hi> may alter this <hi>imaginary appearance</hi> of evill in an action. Reſervation of the brazen ſerpent, as for other ends and purpoſes, ſoe for comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of that miraculous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of the Iſraelites there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, from the ſtings of fierie Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, was for a while free from all ſuſpition, either of idolatrie, or ſuperſtition: but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> once it became the generall, ordinary, nay daily occaſion, and object of idolatry, of the groſſeſt, and moſt palpable kinde of idolatry that can be, when incenſe was offered to it: then if the publicke Magiſtrate had not demoliſhed it, hee might juſtly have beene thought to favour that Idolatry wherewith it was polluted. And therefore commendable was <hi>Hezekiah</hi> his zeale in brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it in pieces. 2. <hi>Kings. c.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 4. and yet the ſame <hi>Hezekiah</hi>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:3506:43"/>did not deſtroy the high places which <hi>Solomon</hi> had built for <hi>Aſhtoreth,</hi> the abomination of the Sidonians; and for <hi>Chemoſh,</hi> the abomination of the Moa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites; and for <hi>Milchom,</hi> the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination of the children of <hi>Ammon;</hi> and yet was never taxed for countenancing of ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry. For in his daies the Idolls there erected, were diſregarded, no man worſhipping them, and therefore might ſafely be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to ſtand; but when after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they were generally, and uſually adored, then the good King <hi>Joſiah</hi> juſtly demoliſhed them; and indeed, ſhould hee have permitted them then, when the Idolatrie, wherewith they were defiled, was flagrant at the height, he might juſtly be ſuſpected to be a favourer of that Idolatry.
<note n="2" place="margin">Kings. <hi>c.</hi> 23. v. 13, 14.</note> Some ceremonies uſed by us now, might have perhaps to the weaker ſort an appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Idolatry, and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before the reformation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:3506:43"/>when the publicke and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed uſe of them was imployd in ſuperſticious ſervices: but now after the reformation, ſince all ſuch uſe of them is by our Church diſavowed, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quite contrary profeſſed, there is no colour for faſtning any ſuch imputation on them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we muſt diſtinguiſh of places. That which in ſome place carries a ſhew of evill, elſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where perhaps is not ſuſpected thereof. Of the cuſtome of thrice dipping in baptiſme, an hereticall conſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was made in Spaine and Africa, but for ought we read, not any where elſe. The Saturday Faſt in the Eaſterne Church, was ſeverely forbidden, becauſe thought to give countenance to the damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and blaſphemous opinion of ſome heretickes, who eſteemed God who made the world, to be the author of evill, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in diſhonour of the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his creation, preſſed faſting
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:3506:44"/>on Saturday, upon which the Jewes feaſted, in memory of the Creation finiſhed. But then the Saturday Faſt was in the Weſterne Church as ſtrictly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, becauſe there feaſting on that day would have counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenced the Jewiſh Solemne ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the old Sabbath as Feſtivall. Bringing of Cakes and Wine into the Church was in Africa uſuall, and inoffenſive, but yet in Millaine by <hi>Ambroſe</hi> prohibited <hi>Monica,</hi> becauſe there it was eſteemed to have much reſemblance of the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentalia,</hi> offerings of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, which were made at the tombes of their Parents,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neritis, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit, ejus morem ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, ſipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum non vultis, aut facere.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. e<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> .86.</note> and to their Ghoſts. According to pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces therefore, in indifferent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters wee may vary our practice. It was the adviſe of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> unto <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and <hi>Monica</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected by <hi>Auſtin,</hi> as if it had beene the anſwer of an heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Oracle; into whatſoever Church yee ſhall come obſerve
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:3506:44"/>the manner, or cuſtome thereof, if yee will neither give nor take ſcandall. And beſides, we have <hi>Pauls</hi> precept, and preſident for it; his precept, 1. <hi>Cor. c.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 32. Give none offence neither to Jew nor Gentile, which could not be done, but by complying with them in indifferencies. His preſident alſo anſwereth his precept; to the Jewes hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Jew, to them that were under the law, as under the law; to them that were without the law, as without the law; to the weake, as weake, 1 <hi>Cor. c.</hi> 9. <hi>v.</hi> 20, 21, 22. Amongſt the Jewes he ſhaved his head, made a vow, <hi>Acts. c.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 18. and circumciſed <hi>Timothy, Acts. c.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 3. And yet amongſt the Gentiles where theſe actions bore an appearance of Judaiſme, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e withſtood <hi>Peter</hi> for them even to his face. <hi>Galat. chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſe</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>After theſe limitations of the dutie of abſtinence from all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:3506:45"/>of evill; I cannot but wonder at our irregulars miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>application of it. They hence eagerly cry downe the laudable diſcipline, and lawfull ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of our Church. What fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full outcries do they make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their appearance of idolatrie, ſuperſtition, will-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Popery? Tearmes you ſee by the exceptions put to this precept, as much too bigge for our innocent and harmeleſſe ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, as <hi>Hercules</hi> ſhooe for a childs foot. Indeed our cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, for example, the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſſe, Croſſe in Baptiſme, knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at the Lords Supper, may have a materiall ſemblance with thoſe that in Popery have been abuſed to idolatie, and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo conſequently taken <hi>materially,</hi> in reſpect of their materials may have an outward ſhew of Popiſh idolatry, or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition; but conſider them as impoſed by our Church, and generally uſed by her members,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:3506:45"/>ſo they are <hi>formally</hi> differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from thoſe which Papiſts have applied to idolatrous ends, and purpoſes. For our Church publickely profeſſeth a quite contrary uſe, or application, end, or intention of them. And ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall actions have their ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, and conſequently di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction from their end and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, from it they take their ſpecies, or kinde, and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are diſtinguiſhed. Now ſince all Popiſh, whether ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous or idolatrous abuſes of our ceremonies, are publickly diſcla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, &amp; their right uſe explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; who can juſtly imagine any ſhew of Popery in them? An Iſraelite was not to be ſmitten for an Egiptian, becauſe for a while hee once ſojourned into Egypt, if afterward hee had his conſtant abode in Canaan. The garment ſpotted with the fleſh was no longer to be hated, than ſpotted; being once waſhed, it might againe be uſed. Our cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:3506:46"/>were defiled in Egypt, in Popery with ſuperſtition, and idolatrie; but our Church (God be praiſed,) hath waſhed them from both in her publicke, and profeſſed uſe of them. And therefore now they ſtand above either calumnie, or ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But I paſſe on to the ſecond thing I propoſed,
<note n="2" place="margin">Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</note> the <hi>Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> of the point. Firſt ſee it backt by conſonant places of Scripture. <hi>Solomon</hi> adviſeth his young man to walke <hi>cautè,</hi> as well as <hi>caſtè,</hi> not to come nigh the doore of the ſtrange-wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans houſe, <hi>Prov. c.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 8. This had not evilneſſe reall, but onely the appearance of evill, as being in a corrupt minde, an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centive</hi> to <hi>uncleaneneſſe,</hi> and in beholders an occaſion of jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and ſuſpicions. Now from <hi>Solomons</hi> interdicting this appearance of evill in ſpeciall, we may by way of Analogie &amp; proportion inferre a fitneſſe of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:3506:46"/>forbearing all in generall. Unto this is analogically applyed the Nazarites preciſe abſtinence fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wine, <hi>Num. c.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4.
<note place="margin">Gutier de Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>io <hi>upon my Text.</hi>
               </note> The Nazarite, as you may ſee there, was to abſtaine from wine, from vineger of wine, from any liquor of grapes, from the materials of wine grapes, from moiſt grapes, from dryed grapes, from all that is made of the vine tree, from not onely the kernell, but even the huske of the grape. The Jewes have added, they were not to come nigh a vineyard. With a ſemblable ſtrictneſſe are we to ſeparate from ſinne, from all ſinnes, ſmall as well as great; from all of ſinne, not onely from the kernell of ſinne, from a ſinne really ſo, but alſo from the husk, the appearance of ſinne. The children of Iſrael were charged not to doe like the heathen that were round about them, 2 <hi>King. chap.</hi> 17. <hi>verſe</hi> 15. where they are interdicted not onely <hi>ſame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> with,
<note place="margin">Exod. 23.13.</note> but alſo <hi>likeneſſe</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:3506:47"/>to their faſhions; they were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden the faſhion of rounding their heads, &amp; cutting their fleſh, of marring the corners of their beards, of making any baldneſſe upon their heads, or betweene their eyes. <hi>Levit. c.</hi> 19. <hi>verſe</hi> 28. <hi>&amp; chap.</hi> 21. <hi>verſe</hi> 25. <hi>Deut. ch.</hi> 14. <hi>verſe</hi> 1. Not becauſe ſo to doe was ſimply in its owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture a ſinne, but for that it gave ſhew of a ſinne, of inordinate ſorrow for the departed; of which 'twas then an expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on much in uſe amongſt the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o Cardinalis,</hi> upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lleageth <hi>Hoſea chap.</hi> 2 <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 6. <hi>Thou ſhalt call mee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhalt call mee no more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> The Gentiles gave the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Baal,</hi> ſo alſo of <hi>Baalim,</hi> unto their great and common Idoll god, ſuppoſed to be the Sunne, and to all the ſeverall i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages <hi>&amp;</hi> repreſentations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And therefore God prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited application of that title unto himſelfe: in worſhip and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:3506:47"/>invocation, Thou ſhalt no more call me, <hi>O my Baal:</hi> for though there be no harme in the word, (it ſignif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing in common uſe, <hi>husband,</hi> as well as <hi>Iſhi,</hi>) yet by reaſon of the ordinary applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof unto Idols, there would have beene an invocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God by that name, a groſſe, and palpable appearance of Idolatry.</p>
            <p>But becauſe it may be excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that moſt of theſe rigid, and ſevere prohibitions were given unto the Jewes under their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagogie of ceremonies, and time of bondage, and therefore farther than in a morall admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion lay noe reſtraint upon us Chriſtians. See therefore all this ſeconded in the New Teſtament by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Jude verſe</hi> 23. Where in reference to that legall pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, which came by touching the garment of one that was Levitically uncleane, he exhorts Chriſtians to <hi>hate the garment ſpotted by the fleſh,</hi> that is, ſaith
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:3506:48"/>
               <hi>Gualter, quicquid ingenium car nis ſapit,</hi> whatſoever hath but a ſmacke or reliſh of the fleſh, all preparations and acceſſaries of evill,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Locus hic, qui obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus alioqui vid tur, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil habebit difficult at is met aphorâ benè expl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catâ; vult fideles, non tantum cavere à vitiorum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tactu, ſed ne qua ad eos co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tagio perting at, quicqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d affine eſt, ac vic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>num fugiendum eſse admonet, quem admodum ſi de pudicitia ſermo habetur d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cemus tol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enda eſſe omnta libid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> irritamenta, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d etiamnum clar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> fiet, ſi amplietur oratio, nempe ut oder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mus non carnem modo ſed tunicam, qua ejus contactu infecta ſit, Nam particula <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ad ampliationem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alet, ergo adeo non permittit indulgen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a fovere, uti omnes praparatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, omn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aque acceſſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a (ut vocant) pot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us reſecar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> jubeat,</hi> Calv. in locum.</note> any thing that is neere of kin unto, or but bordring up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vice, thinkes* <hi>Calvin.</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve here the emphaticall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Apoſtle, hate not onely the fleſh, but the garment ſpotted by the fleſh, not onely overſpread, quite covered, but the garment that was but here and there a little ſpotted by the fleſh. Out of Chriſts garment there iſſued vertue, which cured the woman that had the bloody fluxe, but contrariwiſe out of this garment, but ſpotted with
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:3506:48"/>the fleſh, <hi>Exit vis quaedam ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligna,</hi> there goeth a poiſonous kinde of infection which ſoone will ſtaine a ſoule with the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profie of ſinne. But becauſe (as the old ſaying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unnes) <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xis ſanctorum eſt interpres pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceptorum,</hi> I ſhall intreat you next to take notice how this precept hath beene exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
            <p>And here in the times before Chriſt is very remarkable the couragious and undaunted reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of Eleazar, againſt but the appearance of an evill. 2 <hi>Mac. c.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>v.</hi> 18. <hi>uſque ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inem:</hi> when he was beſought to bring fleſh of his owne proviſion, ſuch as was lawfull for him to uſe, and but make as if hee did eate of the fleſh, taken from the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice commanded by the King <hi>v.</hi> 21. why? even this evill ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, this ſeeming, this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as if he did eate of the fleſh taken from the Sacrifice com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the King, ſoe deeply
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:3506:49"/>diſreliſhed him, as that hee choſe death before it. For it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth not our age (ſaith he) in any wiſe to diſſemble, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by many young perſons might thinke that <hi>Eleazar</hi> being four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore yeares old and ten, was now gone to a ſtrange religion; and ſo they through mine hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, and deſire to live a little time, &amp; a moment longer, ſhould be deceived by mee, and I get a ſtaine to my old age, and make it abominable, <hi>v.</hi> 24, 25. But why mention I <hi>Eleazar?</hi> Behold the example of one greater than <hi>Eleazar,</hi> the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the rule and patterne of holineſſe unto the Church, Chriſt Jeſus, God bleſſed for ever! whoſe example in Morals &amp; matters of ordinary obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence amounts ever unto the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of a command. How exemplarie he was in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular you may reade, <hi>Mat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> c.</hi> 7. from <hi>v.</hi> 24. unto the end of the Chapter. There you have him
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:3506:49"/>performing an action, not for that omiſſion of it would have beene evill, but becauſe in opi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nion of the Jewes, it would have given ſhew of evill. For if firſt, you underſtand the words, as moſt Interpreters doe, of the tribute to be paid unto the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Magiſtrate, then ſinfull it had not been in our Saviour to have refuſed payment of tribute unto <hi>Caeſar.</hi> For how could the Son to the living God (who was King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, King of Heaven, and Earth, whoſe the earth, &amp; all the fulneſſe thereof was) be juſtly tributary unto any mortall? The Kings of the earth take tribute, or cuſtome, not of their owne children, (however they expect obedience from them) but of ſtrangers; becauſe paying of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute denoteth ſome degree, or kinde of ſervitude. The <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren then are free. verſe</hi> 25, 26. Therefore from all taxes, and impoſitions, juſtly was to be
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:3506:50"/>exempted Chriſt, the ſonne of <hi>David,</hi> there was no reaſon hee ſhould pay tribute unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> nay more reaſon (hee being of the blood royall) ſhould receive tribute from the Jewes, than <hi>Caeſar,</hi> a forrainer, having no title to the Crowne, but that which the ſword gave him, not payment, conſtant deniall of payment had not been (you ſee) morally evill in our Saviour; and yet becauſe it would have borne appearance of an evill, of diſloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie, and diſobedience, and ſo have drawn prejudices againſt, and ſcandall upon his unſpotted perſon, holy, and heavenly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and doctrine, becauſe ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly it would have croſſed a doctrine hee afterwards delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>Render unto Caeſar the things which are Caeſars:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee ſtands not to plead his priviledge, but voluntarily par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with his right, payed the tribute, and to pay it wrought a miracle; <hi>notwithſtanding, Peter,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:3506:50"/>leaſt wee ſhould offend them, goe thou to the ſea, and caſt an hooke, and take up the fiſh that firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth up, and when thou haſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened his mouth, thou ſhalt finde a peece of money, that take, and give unto them for mee and thee. verſe</hi> 27.</p>
            <p>Or if ſecondly, with the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Cameron,</hi> you rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to be here meant the halfe ſhekel, which by preſcript of the Ceremoniall Law, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30, was by the Jewes to be paid for the uſe of the Sanctuary. Why yet ſo alſo ſinfull it had not been in our Saviour to have refuſed paying of it: for firſt, it was a ceremony, and the Ceremoniall Law Chriſt was above. Lord he was of the Sabbath, <hi>Mat. c.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 8. <hi>Marke. c.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 28. where it is manifeſt (thinkes <hi>Cameron</hi>) the Sabbath ſhould Synecdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chically ſignifie the whole Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall Law. Then ſecondly, this ceremony, together with Sacrifices and all other Legall,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:3506:51"/>typicall ceremonies preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſinne in the partie, to whom they were commanded, and were a note, or badge of the bondage contracted by ſinne; and therefore reach not unto Chriſt, a man without ſinne. Thirdly, as our Saviour well ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, even as Kings of the Earth take not tribute of their owne Children, ſo neither the King of heaven of his ſonne: therefore ſeeing this halfe ſhekel is a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to be paid to the King of Heaven, for the Tabernacle of Witneſſe, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24.6. Chriſt was certainly free, and ſo might lawfully have refuſed to pay it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet becauſe the Jewes would have taken offence, and at ſuch his refuſall, and charg'd it with appearance of a profane con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the Sanctuary: therefore he vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily paid it, and ſo became a Jewe to the Jewes, as under the Law to them that were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the law. Notwithſtanding,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:3506:51"/>
               <hi>leſt we ſhould offend,</hi> &amp;c. And if this be the ſenſe of the place, what is ſaid of this one ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, may be applyed unto all, for one of the reaſons &amp; ends, why Chriſt obſerved the whole Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall Law was, to prevent ſcandall, to abſtaine from all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of evill. In nature, ſaith <hi>Cameron,</hi> there is <hi>appetitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quidem unionis,</hi> which cauſeth things to be moved, and to reſt often beſides the proper condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their particular nature, whence ſometimes light things are moved downewards, heavie things upwards. Unto this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite of union in nature, there is anſwerable in grace, the deſire <hi>to promote Gods glory,</hi> which often inclineth, and carrieth the godly beyond and beſides the ordinary <hi>obligations, ariſing out of their particular, and perſonall conditions and relations.</hi> And un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the meaſure of grace is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable the degree of the deſire of Gods glory, ſo that the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:3506:52"/>holier any one is, the more ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently hee deſireth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion thereof, and if it require any thing to bee done of him, why he will doe it, although o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſe by vertue of his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and perſonall condition, hee be not bound thereunto. Therefore although Chriſt, <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum ſpecialem rationem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonae ſuae,</hi> if we eye the ſpeciall conſideration, and <hi>dignitie</hi> of <hi>his perſon,</hi> was not tied to keepe the Ceremoniall Law, yet hee kept it in as much as the glory of God required him ſo to doe. If you demand how the glorie of God exacted this at Chriſts hands, why Chriſt himſelfe tels us, <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſimus illis ſca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dalo,</hi> leſt wee ſhould offend them; for if Chriſt had not obſerved the Ceremoniall Law, he had doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe wonderfully eſtranged the Jewes from him. In obſerving it then he did but as Kings often doe in ſtooping to many things, unto which they are no wayes
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:3506:52"/>obliged for to winne the hearts, and affections of their humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſubjects. This example of our Saviour was followed by the Apoſtles, and Elders in the firſt generall Councell at Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, where they impoſed upon the Gentiles abſtinence from meate <hi>offered to Idols, from things ſtrangled, and from blood, Act.</hi> 15.29. Not for that theſe meates were in themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, and abominable, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they appeared to be ſo unto the froward, and peeviſh Jewes, who were kept off from Chriſts, becauſe theſe meats, in which they ſuppoſed to be ſuch abomination, and uncleaneneſſe, were uſually eaten by the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. But this was but a <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary injunction</hi> they gave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others. Let us view their owne practice. Maintenance for preaching was due unto <hi>Paul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> from both the Corinthians, and Theſſalonians, and yet hee did forbeare exacting it, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.1.
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:3506:53"/>
               <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. that ſo hee might take away all colour for ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any mercenary, or greedy appetite after gaine, to be in his preaching, and quite cut off all ſcandals thereby, which in that dawning of Chriſtianitie upon them, would have put a <hi>rubbe</hi> unto the <hi>progreſſe</hi> of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, &amp; have made his miniſtery to be evill ſpoken of. And of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> the Saints in ſucceeding ages were followers, as hee of Chriſt. Thoſe <hi>Libellatici,</hi> ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and ſharply cenſured by <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ciprian, Epiſt.</hi> 15.31.52. <hi>lib. de lapſis. lib. de exhortatione Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrum:</hi> though they did not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, or directly denie Chriſt, were yet by the Church put to their penance, for ſeeming to denie him, becauſe they either by themſelves, or others, at leaſt accepted from the Magiſtrate bills, or ſcroules teſtimoniall of their abnegation.
<note n="*" place="margin">Baronius <hi>out of</hi> Sui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das.</note> 
               <hi>Auxentius</hi> being commanded by <hi>Licinius</hi> to ſet a branch of a vine-tree
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:3506:53"/>loaden with cluſters at the feete of <hi>Bacchus</hi> his image preſently ſhaped him this round, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute anſwer, God forbid, O Emperour, that I ſhould doe it, for I am a Chriſtian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was not great in it ſelfe, yet becauſe it would have favoured Idolatry, or given manifeſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of it, rather than doe it hee choſe baniſhment from the Court, and loſſe of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours ſervice.
<note n="*" place="margin">Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret lib. 3 cap. 15 Ni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cepho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us lib. 11. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 6. c. 6.</note> As <hi>Valentinian,</hi> afterwards Emperour, went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate into a Temple of the Goddeſſe For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, one of the Prieſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprinkled <hi>Julian</hi> with a kinde of purging or holy-water, a drop of which by chance fell on <hi>Valentinian,</hi> at which hee was ſo extreamely incenſed, as that he ſtroake the Prieſt, tore, and rent in peeces that part of his garment on which it fell, with a great diſdaine, and holy indignation, throwing it away from him, that ſo hee might
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:3506:54"/>avoid the leaſt tincture of their ſuperſtitious, and idolatrous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.
<note n="*" place="margin">Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret lib. 4. c. 15. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cephorus l. 11. c 21.</note> But above all, very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable is the zeale of the boyes of Samoſatene, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a tenniſ-ball, with which they played, had but touched the foote of the Aſſe whereon <hi>Lucius</hi> rode, their Hereticall Biſhop, they preſently cryed out that it was defiled (although in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it was not capable of any morall pollution,) and therefore to purge or expiate it threw it into the fire in the midſt of the market place. This may bee thought but a childiſh pranke, and therefore not imitable, however yet it aptly ſerves to demonſtrate that their educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, framed them unto a hatred of whatſoever had any remote reference, unto either evill acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or perſons. Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> forbad <hi>Monica</hi> the bringing of wine and cakes to the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brities of the Martyrs, not for any unlawfulneſſe of the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:3506:54"/>but <hi>nè <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> occaſio ſe ingur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> daretur ebrioſis, &amp; qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> illa quaſi parent alia ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Gentilium eſſent ſimillima,</hi> as Saint <hi>Auſtin lib.</hi> 6. <hi>confeſſ. c.</hi> 2. leaſt occaſion of exceſſive quaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſhould be given to drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, and becauſe thoſe <hi>paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talia,</hi> funerall feaſts, were very like to heatheniſh ſuperſtition. A reverend Prelate of our Church, aſſignes another rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe this cuſtome, had ſome reſemblance of thoſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious and idolatrous Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rydians mentioned by <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius,</hi> who offered cakes to the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> in imitation of that heatheniſh cuſtome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by the Prophet <hi>Jeremy, chap.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 18. of ſuch as did offer cakes unto the Moone, as unto the Queene of heaven. Now when <hi>Monica</hi> underſtood that Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> had forbidden this <hi>tam piè, atque obedienter amplexa eſt, ut ipſe mirarer,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> in that forecited
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:3506:55"/>place. <hi>Quod tam facilè accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix potius conſuetudinis ſuae quam diſceptatrix illius prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitionis effecta ſit:</hi> ſhe ſo piouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and obediently embraced this prohibition as that I my ſelfe, ſaith <hi>Auſtin,</hi> wondered to ſee her ſo eaſily rather accuſe her owne cuſtome, than diſpute his command. The cuſtome of thrice dipping or ſprinkling in Baptiſme was <hi>lawfull</hi> nay <hi>lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable,</hi> but when once it was uſed by Heretickes, to ſignifie a Trinitie not of <hi>perſons,</hi> but <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> in the Godhead, then Saint <hi>Gregory</hi> thought fitting that it ſhould be left of, not becauſe it was evill, but for that it might ſeeme to countenance their damnable Hereſie: his words are theſe, <hi>de trina verò merſione baptiſmatis nihil responderi ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius poteſt, quam quod ipſi ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, quoà in una ſide nihil officit ſanctae Eccleſiae conſuetudo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſa, &amp;c. ſed quia nunc huc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſque ab haereticis infans in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmate
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:3506:55"/>tertiò mergebatur, faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum apud vos eſſe non cenſeo,
<note place="margin">Lib 1. c. 3. <hi>In ipſo ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulo pon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur</hi> Divi Paul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>pro</hi> Beati Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, <hi>ego enim nunquam proba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus, vel Diva, cum de Sanctis agitur, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> quod eam voce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apud La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>nos vetere Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniam, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> quod apud E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cos Div<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> nome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bui ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> ne dum merſiones numerant di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitatem dividant, dum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> quod faciebant faciunt, ſe morem no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum viciſſe glorientur. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 41. <hi>Gabriel Biel lectione</hi> 38. ſaith, that the Church of Rome thought it meete to uſe common leavened bread in the adminiſtration of the Euchariſt, leſt in uſing unleavened bread, they ſhould be deemed to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate <hi>Ebion</hi> the hereticke: Nay <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his recognition of his booke <hi>de verbo Dei,</hi> admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth the reader, that in the title of the third Chapter of the firſt books <hi>Divi Pauli</hi> is put for <hi>Beati Pauli,</hi> for in making men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Saints, I never ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved (ſaith hee) the uſe of the word * <hi>divus</hi> or <hi>diva,</hi> &amp; one of his reaſons is, becauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the heathens, 'twas uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally aſcribed to <hi>their falſe or fained gods.</hi> But what meane I to alleage the examples of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:3506:56"/>the Chuch of Rome, or <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> for take wee but a view of our owne Church, the lives of her Worthies, will yeeld ſtore of preſidents in this kinde, but I will content my ſelfe with one, moſt eſpecially deſerving our notice, and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. And it is the religious care that King <hi>James</hi> of bleſſed memory had, to free, and cleare our booke of Common-prayer, not onely from faultineſſe in it ſelfe, but alſo offenſiveneſſe unto men, and by cauſing an explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be made of thoſe things in it, which were excepted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt: how carefull, and ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous he was in this particular, you may read in his Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion prefixed to the booke of Common prayer, wee thought meete, faith hee there, that ſome ſmall things might bee explai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, not that the ſame might not very well have beene borne with by men, who would have made a reaſonable conſtruction
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:3506:56"/>of them, but for that in a matter concerning the ſervice of God, we were nice, or rather jealous, that the publicke forme thereof ſhould be free, not onely from <hi>blame,</hi> but from <hi>ſuſpicion,</hi> ſo as neither the common adverſary ſhould have advantage to wreſt ought therein contained to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſe, than the Church of England intendeth, nor any troubleſome, or ignorant perſon of his Church, be able to take the leaſt occaſion of cavill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To heape up other, either te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies, or inſtances, were to prejudice, if not the <hi>authoritie</hi> of thoſe before mentioned, yet your <hi>eſteeme</hi> of them, as if you were not by them ſufficiently perſwaded and convinced: my labour (I ſuppoſe) will be better ſpent in demonſtrating unto you the <hi>expediencie</hi> of that which may ſeeme rigour in this doctrine, in diſcovering unto you what good reaſons Saint
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:3506:57"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> had to exact ſo great a meaſure, and ſo high a pitch of abſtinence from ſinne. Thoſe that I will ſpecifie ſhall bee drawne from <hi>God,</hi> from <hi>Satan,</hi> from our <hi>ſelves,</hi> from our <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> Firſt from God, wee have theſe two, our <hi>Relations unto him, our Danger in offending of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt our <hi>Relations unto him,</hi> he is our <hi>Father,</hi> our <hi>Soveraigne; Chriſt Jeſus is our spirituall Husband</hi> Now a dutifull child declines not only diſobedience, but whatſoever hath the colour of it; an obedient, and loyall ſubject, ſtartles at not onely <hi>treaſon,</hi> but alſo whatſoever may occaſion <hi>ſuſpicion</hi> thereof; a <hi>faithfull</hi> &amp; <hi>chaſt wife</hi> abhorres not onely <hi>adultery,</hi> but whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may make her husband <hi>juſtly jealous,</hi> others but <hi>ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> of her <hi>chaſtity.</hi> And ſhall not every child of God, every one that profeſſeth ſubjection unto heaven, be fearfull of the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:3506:57"/>of diſobedience, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutifulneſſe to ſo indulgent a <hi>Father as God,</hi> of the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Treaſon and Rebellion againſt ſo Almightie a <hi>King as God?</hi> Doth it not befit the <hi>Spouſe</hi> the Church, every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſt to dread all ſhews and ſignes of <hi>diſloyalty,</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſſe to ſoe loving a Spouſe as <hi>Chriſt Jeſus?</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Sueton, de Jul. Caeſar. c. 74.</note> Did <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> but an earthly Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate, thinke it not enough that his wife was without a fault, unleſſe withall ſhee was without ſo much as the ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a fault? And will not Chriſt (thinke you?) who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, expect as great un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameableneſſe in his Spouſe?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plutarch in the life</hi> Pompey.</note> 
               <hi>Theophanes Lesbian</hi> to diſwade <hi>Pompey</hi> from flying into Parthia tels him that his wife would be liable to a great deale of danger amongſt thoſe barbarous peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and though (ſaid hee) they proffer no villany unto her, yet
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:3506:58"/>it is an undecent thing to thinke that the wife of <hi>Pompey</hi> might have beene diſhonoured: To di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wade us from the appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and occaſions of ſinne it ſhould (me thinkes) be an effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall argument, that our ſoules which are married unto Chriſt in righteouſneſſe, judgement, and holineſſe, will hereby bee obnoxious to danger of polluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; what though they be not actually defiled? yet it is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decent thing to thinke that the ſpouſe, a member of Chriſt might have beene diſhonoured, might have beene foyl'd with a luſt, raviſhed, vanquiſhed by Satan, defiled with ſinne.</p>
            <p>If from theſe appearances of evill, our <hi>Relations</hi> to God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>draw</hi> us, yet (mee thinkes) in the ſecond place, our <hi>danger</hi> in offending of him ſhould <hi>drive us,</hi> for hee is a conſuming fire unto, as the <hi>workes,</hi> ſo alſo the <hi>workers</hi> of impiety: and how can wee then but be afraid to
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:3506:58"/>venture on not onely what we know doth, but what we feare, others ſuſpect may deſerve the wrath of ſo ſinne-revenging a God?</p>
            <p>That we ſhould abſtaine from all appearance of evill, may ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly be gathered from <hi>Satan,</hi> from the conſideration, firſt, of his <hi>crueltie</hi> and <hi>malice</hi> againſt us, Secondly, of his <hi>temptations</hi> of us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, from the conſideration of his <hi>cruelty</hi> and <hi>malice</hi> againſt us, which the Scripture ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doweth out by terming him,
<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 13.39.</note> the <hi>Enemy,</hi> by way of excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, the
<note n="b" place="margin">Rev. 12.10. Rev. 9.11. Malach. 3.11. Joh 8.44. 1. Joh. 3.15. 1 Pet. 5.8. Rev. 12.9.</note> 
               <hi>envious man, the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſar,</hi> the <hi>Tempter,</hi> the <hi>Deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> the <hi>Devourer,</hi> a <hi>Murtherer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning;</hi> as alſo by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring him unto a <hi>roaring Lyon,</hi> unto a <hi>great red Dragon, an old</hi> Serpent. Now me-thinkes we ſhould feare to come, not onely under the power, but alſo into the ſight of ſuch an adverſary: and yet by ruſhing upon the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:3506:59"/>ſhewes, the occaſions of evill, what do we but hazard the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizall of our ſoules by him?</p>
            <p>This will be more apparent, from the conſideration, 2, of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans temptations</hi> of us: of his Temptations of us to <hi>ſinne,</hi> of his Temptations of us to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spaire,</hi> or at leaſt diſcomfort, for ſinne; becauſe in both ſorts of temptations hee goes about by theſe appearances of evill, to wreake his malice upon us.</p>
            <p>For firſt, in his temptations of us to ſinne, they are firſt the <hi>bate</hi> by which hee <hi>allures:</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, an <hi>argument</hi> by which hee <hi>perſwades</hi> us thereunto. Thirdly, an encouragement, whereby he is heart'ned to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in tempting of us.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, the appearances of ſinne, are a <hi>baite</hi> whereby Satan allures us unto ſin, which if wee bite at, our conſciences will ſoone be enlarged to ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſinne it ſelfe. Satan well knowing that Gods children
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:3506:59"/>would even ſtartle at your groſſe and more hideous ſinnes, ſuch as are Idolatry, Adultery, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the like, therefore chiefly plyeth them with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticements to the ſignes, ſhewes, and occaſions of them, for theſe will ſmooth the paſſage unto the ſinnes themſelves. Of this we have a remarkeable inſtance in <hi>Alippius,</hi> who, as Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> relates <hi>Confeſſ. lib. 6. cap.</hi> 8. being drawne by his friend's im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie to accompany him unto the Roman Gladiatorie Games, yet reſolved though he were preſent with his body, to be abſent in his heart, and for that purpoſe to keepe his eyes ſhut, that hee might not defile them with ſo barbarous a ſight; yet at laſt upon a great ſhout, that the people gave at the fall of one of the combatants, his curioſitie made him behold the occaſion, and thereupon hee preſenly became an applauſive ſpectator of that bloudy, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:3506:60"/>ſpectacle. An Italian, as <hi>Holerius</hi> writes, by his often ſmelling to the hearbe Baſile, had a ſcorpion ingendred in his head: even ſo we, by our often dallying, and tampering with things that carry a ſhew of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfulneſſe, may have Satan, as I may ſo ſpeake, even formed in us, for as then Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ſaith upon <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> the ninth, <hi>Diabolus Serpens eſt Lubricus, cujus ſi capiti, id eſt, primae ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtioni non reſiſtitur, totus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terna cordis, dum non ſentitur illabitur,</hi> that is, the Divell is a ſlippery ſerpent, and if wee doe not keepe out his head, that is, his firſt ſuggeſtions, it is not to be doubted but that hee will ſteallingly ſlide into the moſt ſecret corners of the heart; and ſo wee actuated by him, ſhall at laſt proceed from things onely appearing ſinfull, unto the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of moſt horrid and ghaſtly crimes,</p>
            <p>Secondly, the appearance of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:3506:60"/>evill is an argument by which he perſwades us unto what is in its owne nature evill: for if a man have but ſlipt into ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions as the beſt minded judge, to have a reall appearance of evill. Satan forthwith will ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt unto him, that hee hath by this quite crackt his credit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe that are accounted religious; by them (will he ſay) thou art as much ſuſpected, and as deepely conſured for thy ſeeming evill, as for thy being ſo; wert thou not better there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, be as thou ſeemeſt, for they cannot think worſe of thee than they doe, thy ſhame and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace their jealouſies, ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and cenſures cannot be greater for ſinne it ſelfe, than it is already for the ſhow of it. Now this Temptation of Satan receives great advantage from our nature, for we naturally are addicted to ſociety, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if wee finde that upon the ſignes and ſhewes of ſuch and
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:3506:61"/>ſuch ſinnes in our practice, good men condemne us as guilty of the ſinnes themſelves, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon begin to reſerve and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrange themſelves fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> us, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing any lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to reach out unto us the right hand of fellowſhip, why, then wee will preſently have fellowſhip with the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull workes of darkeneſſe, and couple in with looſe, carnal, and formall men, whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation will quickly infect us, ſo that it will not be long ere we runne with them to the ſame exceſſe of riot. And thus you ſee how Satan takes occaſion from the appearance of ſinne, to draw us on unto ſinne it ſelfe, which me-thinkes ſhould be ſufficient to diſſwade us from them. For is Satan ſo backward in temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or is his invention growne ſo barren, as that our lives and practice muſt put argument into his mouth? is the purchaſe of hell and damnation ſo difficult, as that wee muſt needs furniſh
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:3506:61"/>the Divell with baites to allure us, with reaſons to perſwade us unto our owne everlaſting per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, this were folly and mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that would want a name.</p>
            <p>But in the third place, the ſignes and appearances of ſinne are not onely a baite, by which he <hi>enticeth</hi> us, an argument by which hee <hi>perſwades unto</hi> ſinne, but withall an encouragement, by which he is heart'ned to goe on in tempting of us, for they make him gather heart, &amp; hope that wee are comming on to ſin it ſelfe; and this hope will breed diligence, make him a more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate ſolliciter, make him to double and ſtrengthen his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults, to ply us even thicke &amp; three-fold with temptations: A dog will not run from a man as long as he throwes bread unto him, and can any man ſuppoſe the divell will flye ſo long as he gives place unto him, as long as he throwes himſelfe upon tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, by practiſing ſuch
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:3506:62"/>things as have a manifeſt ſhew of evill, for though in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they bee never ſo ſmall, yet will they ſerve to uſher in farther and greater matters: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then preparatives unto ſin, they cannot be (as ſome have imagined) good fences againſt ſinne: ſeeming to be evill is not, cannot be a meanes to ſhield us from being ſo, no more than the opening the gates of a City can be the way to rayſe the ſiege of it, or letting goe the ſluces of a river can be the courſe to ſtop its current.</p>
            <p>You have ſeene arguments from Satans <hi>temptation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of us to ſinne: take next one from his temptations of us to <hi>deſpaire,</hi> or at leaſt diſcomfort for ſinne, a temptation of ſo hideous a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as that me-thinkes our actions ſhould not lend it any the leaſt advantage, his firſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is by the appearance of ſinne to make us offend God, but when he cannot proceed ſo
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:3506:62"/>farre, his ſecond endeavour will bee, to make us diſquiet our ſelves, when hee cannot wound us by them, hee will vexe us for them, for he will wreſt and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtrue all that we have done unto the worſt ſenſe, hee will ſwell motes into beames, mole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hils into mountaines, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of evill into realities, and thunder unto us that there is not a pinne to chooſe betwixt thoſe and theſe; unto which our ſoules being diſtracted by the violent importunitie of this temptation, will be over apt to give credence. And for a man to be thus toſſed betweene Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans powerfull ſuggeſtions, and his owne feares and ſuſpicions, cannot but even cruſh his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and quite ecclipſe the peace and joy of his heart.</p>
            <p>Abſtinence from all appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of evill is thirdly needfull in regard of <hi>our ſelves,</hi> for by them we may incurre a double danger, a <hi>danger</hi> of being <hi>infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:3506:63"/>with,</hi> a danger of being <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, a danger of being infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with ſinne, what <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpake of <hi>Eves</hi> beholding the forbidden fruit, is true concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning every appearance of evill:
<note n="*" place="margin">Bren. Tract. de grad, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militatis.</note> 
               <hi>Et ſi culpa non eſt, culpae tameu indicium eſt, &amp; ſi culpa non eſt, culpae tamen occaſio eſt, indicium commiſſae, &amp; cauſa eſt commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendae.</hi> Although it be not in it ſelfe a ſinne, yet it is a token, yet it is an occaſion of ſinne, a token that ſinne hath beene committed, a cauſe of commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it for the future. Now our natures are ſtrongly bent to evill, when this (then) our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall inclination, is furthered by outward occaſions, wee may ſoone bee led to the reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of ſinne, though the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of themſelves are weake, they working but as objects, and the objective cauſalitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all moſt imperfect, yet Satan is ſtrong, our luſts are
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:3506:63"/>ſtrong, theſe occaſions are ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to our luſts: our ſoules therefore, by a little helpe from Satan will quickly catch infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from them. For this reaſon were the Iſraelites,
<note place="margin">Exod. 12.</note> in the time of the paſſeover prohibited, not onely the eating, but the very having of leavened bread in their houſes. For this reaſon too were the Nazarites forbidden to eate ſo much as the huskes of the grapes, for if that had beene permitted, they would perhaps, have ſoone proceeded to eating of the grapes, and thence to drinking of the wine it ſelfe: hence alſo grew that preciſe reſolution of <hi>David,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 101. v. 3.</note> I will ſet no wicked thing before mine eyes:</hi> Well may the world, and divell ſet wicked things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mine eyes, but for mine owne part I will not invite temptations, <hi>I will ſet no wicked thing before mine eyes,</hi> as much as I can I will decline the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, examples, and ſhewes of
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:3506:64"/>wickedneſſe: doe but put fire unto flaxe and it will preſently be on a flame: ſo preſent wee unto our looſe and corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures the ſhows, (which (as you have heard) are alſo the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of evill) and how ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will they take fire? this <hi>Joſeph</hi> knew, and therefore when his Miſtris ſollicited him to that foule act of uncleanneſſe, hee hearkned not unto her to lye by her, or ſo much as to be with her, <hi>Gen:</hi> the 39. the 10. but fled, and got himſelfe out of her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, <hi>v.</hi> 12. doubting leſt the very ſight of her might kindle luſt. Nay to the ſhame of many ſecure and venterous Chriſtians, of this even <hi>Scipio</hi> an heathen, &amp; ſouldier too, was apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive and fearefull, and therefore would not ſuffer certaine cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive virgins, though of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite beauty, to be brought ſo much as into his preſence: <hi>Ne quid</hi> (ſaith <hi>Florus</hi>) <hi>de virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis integritate delibâſſe, ſaltem
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:3506:64"/>vel oculis videretur.</hi> That hee might not ſeeme to have ſipt or skimmed the honour of their chaſtitie, ſo much as with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding them. As <hi>Appelles</hi> then by drawing the picture of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſpe</hi> fell in love with the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of his worke <hi>Campaſpe</hi> her ſelf, ſo we fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> retaining, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the ſhew of ſin, will ſoone proceed to a delight in fin it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Some indeed are ſo ſtrangely confident of their abhorrencie from ſinne, as they doubt not infection from appearance of it, they can venture into the looſeſt company, yet ſo bridle their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, as that they feare no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe; be preſent at an Idolatrous maſſe, and yet be in no danger of being affected with it, unleſſe it be with diſlike of it.</p>
            <p>Surely theſe men are dropt from heaven, never borne in ſinne, or conceiv'd in iniquity; for they, whoſe originall is from men, may poſſibly be drawne away by ſinfull objects, and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:3506:65"/>ſhews, but theſe men (forſooth) are above gun-ſhot, beyond the reach of temptation; Their profeſſed hatred of ſinne brings me in minde of <hi>Pigmalions</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſſe from women; hee was a profeſt, almoſt a ſworne ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to woman-kinde, yet draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but the picture of a woman, hee fell in love with it, and hee hugg'd, and kiſſ'd it ſo long, till at laſt, by the power of <hi>Venus</hi> (as the Poët fables it) it became a woman: Their caſe is like, they profeſſe deteſtation of ſinne, and yet delight in ſome things that have the appearance, the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance thereof, let them take heed they dote not ſo long upon theſe, at that at length by the power of Satan, &amp; the ſtrength of their owne luſts, they bee transformed into reall ſinnes. I will end this reaſon with that of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> in his fifteenth Homily unto the people of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:3506:65"/>&amp;c.</p>
            <p>It will be to us the occaſion of greateſt ſecurity, if wee do not onely flee ſinnes, but ſuch indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent things alſo, which are meanes whereby they doe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plant us, for as hee who goeth upon the edge of a ſteepe, and craggie rocke, though he falleth not, yet with feare trembleth, and ſo falls through his trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, ſo hee who leaveth not ſinne aloofe, and a farre off, but approacheth cloſe to the brinke of it, hath juſt cauſe to live in feare, ſeeing hee hath juſt cauſe to feare to fall into it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, danger of <hi>being pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for ſin,</hi> not <hi>by God,</hi> for he is an omniſcient Judge, &amp; therefore cannot miſtake the appearance of evill for evill it ſelfe: hee is a juſt Judge, and therefore will not puniſh the appearance of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:3506:66"/>evill, for evill it ſelfe: but <hi>by man,</hi> by the <hi>ſecular Magiſtrate</hi> with temporall puniſhments, by the governours of the Church, with Eccleſiaſticall cenſures, and by all men generally with ſhame and <hi>obloquie. Jehoſaphat</hi> you know in the apparell of <hi>Ahab,</hi> was like to have beene kild for <hi>Ahab.
<note n="*" place="margin">Plutarch.</note> Megaclis</hi> having on the cloake, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of <hi>Pyrrhus,</hi> was ſlaine for <hi>Pyrrhus:</hi> even ſo many times ſome men, for the bare appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſome crimes are as hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thought of, and as ſeverely handled, as if they had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the crimes themſelves.
<note n="*" place="margin">Florus, l. 3. c. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius Gracchus,</hi> was butchered by the Romans, becauſe it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med unto them, that by touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his head with his hand, hee had demanded a Diadem, when he thereby as a ſigne onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted them to ſtand upon their defence. Becauſe the Iſland of Creete ſeemed to have favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Mithridates,</hi> for this ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:3506:66"/>ſake, the people of Rome tooke revenge by the ſword, <hi>Faviſſe Mithridati videbatur,
<note place="margin">Florus l. 3. c. 7.</note> hoc placuit armis vindicare.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Lord ſeeth not as man ſeeth, hee looketh on the heart, and thereunto ſquareth his judgement, but man looketh on the outward appearance 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7. and according to it cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and ſo hee may doe, and yet oftentimes judge righteous judgement, for if when there is wanting ſufficient evidence of fact, Judges and Juries ſhould not ſometimes proceed upon pregnant ſignes, and ſtrong pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions, how many villanies would paſſe unpuniſhed? and if Eccleſiaſticall Governours, ſhould not take the ſame courſe too, how could they poſſibly ſtop the ſpreading miſchiefe of Scandals.</p>
            <p>This abſtinence from appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of evill is laſtly expedient in regard of <hi>our brethren,</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void ſcandall unto them.</p>
            <pb n="128" facs="tcp:3506:67"/>
            <p>Firſt as it is taken by <hi>Thomas</hi> and the Schole-men, for that which occaſionally leads unto ſinne, which puts a ſtumbling blocke, or an occaſion to fall in the way of others, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.13. for ſo doe all evill ſhowes, and that both in the <hi>way</hi> of the <hi>weake,</hi> and in the <hi>way</hi> of the <hi>wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, in the <hi>way</hi> of the <hi>weake,</hi> for they are miſguided, and drawne unto the practice of that evill, the appearance whereof they ſee in us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in the <hi>way</hi> of the <hi>wicked;</hi> for firſt, hereby the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate are heartned, confirmed, and comforted: ſecondly, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon adverſaries take occaſion to ſpeake reproachfully of that holy name, &amp; profeſſion which wee beare, to blaſpheme the Croſſe, Truth, and Goſpell of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as 'tis uſed vulgar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and commonly for forrow, griefe, diſlike, or diſpleaſure at
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:3506:67"/>an action, for it matters not much whether our facts be evill or beare ſhew of evill, they equally would wound the hearts and vexe the righteous ſpirits of the godly, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are both violations of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> precept. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.2. Let every one of us pleaſe his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for his good to edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Valerius Publicola</hi> (ſaith <hi>Florus,</hi>) <hi>ne ſpecie arcis offende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, eminontes aedes ſuas in plano ſubmiſit:</hi> hee levell'd with the ground his high and loftie buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings leſt hee ſhould offend the people with the appearance of a cittadell, and wilt not thou throw aſide a vanitie; an excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſome idle if not monſtrous faſhion, rather than offend thy brother (for whom Chriſt died) with the appearance of an evill. A foule ſhame were it, that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pularity ſhould prevaile more with a Roman, than charity with thee who art a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</p>
            <pb n="130" facs="tcp:3506:68"/>
            <p>But ſome will be ready to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, that this doctrine is preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall to our Chriſtian libertie, for that reacheth to the uſe of all things that are of an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent nature, and ſuch are theſe actions charged with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of evill, and therefore if ye ſtreighten us in the uſe of them, you injuriouſly deprive us of that liberty which wee have in Chriſt Jeſus unto the uſe of all indifferent things.</p>
            <p>Unto this two things are to be anſwered: Firſt, thoſe facts that beare ſhew of evill, howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they bee in <hi>Theſi,</hi> in their generall nature indifferent, doe yet in <hi>in caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and in <hi>Hypotheſi,</hi> become to be accidentally evill, becauſe done againſt conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, when they appeare to be evill unto our ſelves; againſt charity, when they appeare to bee evill unto others. <hi>Zuarez</hi> expreſſeth this though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what obſcurely, yet more fully; An action (ſaith he) only evill in
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:3506:68"/>appearance, tranſgreſſeth ſome vertue not <hi>prima per ſe primò,</hi> but onely <hi>ex conſequenti, conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xione virtutum,</hi> by reaſon of the mutuall connexion, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of one vertue with, and dependance upon another. <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertendum eſt (inquit) duplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter contra aliquam virtutem peccari: uno modo per ſe primo, quia directè agitur contra obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum ejus vel circumſtantias illi ex ſe debitas, &amp; hoc modo actio ſolum mala in apparentia nullam virtutem offendit. Alio modo peccari; poteſt ex conſequenti &amp; connexione virtutum. Nam (ut dictum eſt</hi> 1.2<hi>ae: quia actus vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum ſunt undique boni, quando hic &amp; nunc actus alicujus vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis poteſt eſſe contrarius alteri virtuti (quamvis in objecto ſuo, vel circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantiis quaſi intrinſecis non habeat defectum) non poteſt prudenter fieri; Atque adeo ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eſt actus virtutis ſimpliciter, &amp; ideò participat malitiam contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> utri<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> virtuti, ſed alteram per
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:3506:69"/>ſe, alteram quaſi per accidens &amp; conſequenter. Sic etiam propria malitia ſcandali ferè ſemper fundatur in alia malitia, tamen ex conſequenti &amp; per accidens ſemper habet aliquo modo illam conjuncta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex defectu circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae debitae, ſaltem propter aliam virtutem propter quam non lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendam prudenter ceſſandum eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet ab opere hic &amp; nunc habente ſpeciem mali, quamvis ex ſe eſſet aliàs honeſtum. Zuarez de tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plici virtute Theologica, tract. de charitate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, although our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty extendeth to the uſe of all things indifferent, yet ought wee in godly wiſdome, and diſcretion to abridge our ſelves of the outward exerciſe of this our liberty, whenſoever 'tis very probable that it will become da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous to our ſelves, or ſcandalous to others. Ye have beene called unto liberty, onely uſe not liberty for an occaſion to the fleſh, but by love ſerve
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:3506:69"/>one another, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.13. As free, and not uſing your liberty for a cloake of maliciouſneſſe, the 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.16. Now wee uſe or rather abuſe our liberty for an occaſion to the fleſh for a cloake of maliciouſneſſe, by practiſing ſuch indifferences, as have ſhew of evill, for they, (as you have heard at large) are likely to prove as occaſions of ſinne unto our ſelves, ſo alſo active ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals to miſguide our brethren, and therefore though they be not abſolutely, and ſimply in their nature unlawfull to bee done, yet they are by accident unlawfull for mee to doe, as long as they carry ſhew of evill. All things (indeed) are pure (ſaith the Apoſtle) but it is evill for that man who eateth with of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence:
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinem ad ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio autem nominat indignatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, &amp;c. ſcandalum autem im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portat ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem ad ruinam.</hi> Aquin. 2<hi>a</hi> 2<hi>ae.</hi> q. 44. art. 1.</note> It is good neither to eate fleſh, nor drinke wine, nor any thing whereby thy brother ſtumbleth, or is offended, or is made weake. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.20, 21.</p>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:3506:70"/>
            <p>What remaineth then,
<note place="margin">Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> but that all be admoniſhed in the Lord Jeſus to take to heart a matter ſo deeply concerning them, both in conſcience, as a duty expreſly enjoyned by God, practiſed by Chriſt his Apoſtles, and Saints; and in conſequence, as befitting us as the ſonnes, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of God, as the Spouſe, and members of Chriſt, as beeing needfull to defeat Satans ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, to cut off his temptations unto ſinne, and unto diſcomfort for ſinne, to avoid ſinne, &amp;c: in our ſelves, ſcandalls unto others, unto the weake, obſtinate, and ſtrong. If therefore there be in in you any love of God, any care to walke worthy of thoſe high relations you carry to him, any regard to the ſafety of your owne ſoules, any feare of Satan, ſinne, or puniſhment, any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion over the conſciences of your poore brethren, keepe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loofe from whatſoever neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and borders upon ſinne,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:3506:70"/>whatſoever hath the bluſh and ſhew thereof: hate as
<note n="*" place="margin">Ambr. l. 6 hexaem.</note> 
               <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> exhorts not onely ſinne, but the coate of ſinne, the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſpotted by the fleſh. Even an heathen will adviſe you hereunto.
<note n="*" place="margin">Quint. l. 2 c. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Carendum non ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum crimine turpitudinis, verum etiam ſuſpicione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Want we inducements, take wee theſe three. It will be a courſe, firſt ſafe and ſecure: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, comfortable: thirdly, honourable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>ſafe and ſecure,</hi> by it ſin &amp; Satan ſhall be ſtav'd off, kept out at daggers end, your owne ſoules ſecured, kept out of gun-ſhot either of infection or puniſhment, ſo that they ſhall not come nigh ſcarce ſo much as the confines either of ſinne, or hell. Secondly, <hi>comfortable:</hi> For what an unſpeakable comfort will it be unto thy drooping ſoule in the houre of death, or in the time of ſpirituall deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when thy conſcience can
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:3506:71"/>truly ſuggeſt, that thou haſt beene ſo abhorrent from ſinne, as that thou haſt ſhunn'd what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever hath beene homogeneall thereunto, whatſoever hath looked but like unto it, it muſt needs ſtop Satans mouth, and make thine owne ſoule triumph in the calmeneſſe of a cleare, and good Conſcience.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>honourable,</hi> for 'twill gain thee eſteeme amongſt both <hi>good</hi> and <hi>bad ones,</hi> with thoſe 'twill make thy name precious, 'twill muzzle the mouthes of theſe, when they behold ſuch uprightneſſe in thy life, as that thou ſhunneſt not onely down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right irreligiouſneſſe to God, injuſtice to men, but even their very picture and reſemblance, this cannot but extort from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, though never ſo malicious, an ingenious acknowledgement, that thou art a true Iſraelite, a ſyncere Nathaniel in whom there is found no guile. Now though our maine and firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:3506:71"/>muſt bee to keepe a good conſcience, yet is not the Jewel or precious oyntment of a good name, to be in the meane while neglected; our care ſhould be to preſerve that like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe unſpotted, S. <hi>Paul</hi> (<hi>Acts.</hi> 24.16.) profeſſeth that hee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed himſelfe to have alwaies a conſcience void of offence, as towards God, ſo towards men; and hee adviſeth us to provide things honeſt in the ſight of all men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.17. To walke ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly towards them that are without 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.12. To ſtrive for a good report of them that are without, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.7.</p>
            <p>I will but preſcribe two cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions directing how wee are to abſtaine from the appearance of evill, and then I ſhall have done with the generall application of the words. Wee are to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine neither <hi>onely,</hi> nor <hi>chiefly</hi> from the appearance of evill.</p>
            <p>Firſt, not <hi>only,</hi> that were foule <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> of which yet there
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:3506:72"/>are even a generation guilty, who ouely combate with the ſhadow of ſinne, and in the meane while embrace the body of ſinne, reall ſinnes; who ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from the ſhew of every evill worke, and yet remaine reprobate to every good work, who profeſſe deteſtation of gaine by gaming, becauſe they conceive it to be an appearance of theft, and yet make no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of fraud, deceit, and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenage in their dealings, who ſtand at defiance with all ſhews of uncleanneſſe, and yet make no ſcruple of the groſſeſt acts thereof.</p>
            <p>Secondly, not <hi>chiefly,</hi> that were a great incongruity, for ſo care of the meanes ſhould, be greater than that of the end, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe abſtinence from the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of evill is enjoyned as a preſervative againſt the evill it ſelfe; The evills themſelves therefore ſhould chiefly be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided, the body of ſin ſhould
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:3506:72"/>be oppoſed more than the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, than the ſhewes of ſinne. The fleſh ſhould be abhorred in a higher degree, than the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſpotted therewith.</p>
            <p>You have ſeen the point preſt generally, as it concernes all mens abſtinence from the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of all evills: I will on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly crave your pardon to call more particularly:</p>
            <p>Firſt upon <hi>all men,</hi> for abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from the appearance e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially of <hi>ſome evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, upon <hi>ſome men</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially for abſtinence from the appearance <hi>of all evils,</hi> and then I will put a period to my meditations upon theſe words.</p>
            <p>Firſt wee muſt decline the ſhews of ſome evils above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of our <hi>maſter,</hi> our <hi>boſome evils.</hi> For from them is moſt danger to be feared, they having commonly moſt ſtrength from our natures: and Satan beſides knowes but too well how our tyde ſtands, hee quickly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:3506:73"/>himſelfe with our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant luſts, and moſt raging corruptions, and unto them e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially fits, and accords his temptations; as <hi>Agrippina,</hi> when ſhee poyſoned her husband <hi>Claudius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacitus Suetoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us.</note> mixed the poyſon in the meat which he moſt lov'd.</p>
            <p>Secondly <hi>ſome men</hi> above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are eſpecially to decline the appearance of <hi>all evills.</hi> All publike men ſhould do ſo, but eſpecially wee of the Clergie. The high Prieſts and Nazarites under the Law were not to come nigh a dead body, <hi>Levit.</hi> 21.11. <hi>Num.</hi> 6.6. And in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of them among the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, the Prieſts might not touch the dead, nay they might not ſee the dead; for if a Prieſt pronounced a funerall oration, 'twas not without a veile drawne betwixt him and the corps. Nay a Flaminians Prieſt might not heare the ſound of pipes uſed at Funerals, nor come into a place where there was a
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:3506:73"/>grave. Was there ſuch rituall purity under the Law? Such ceremoniall ſtrictneſſe in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh prieſts? and ſhall there not be found an anſwerable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of morall preciſeneſſe in the Miniſters of the Goſpell? ſhall they bee willingly within ſight, ſent, and hearing of impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, except to reprove it?
<note place="margin">Mr Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nold, Pſal. 110.</note> As a woman bigge with child, for feare and danger of miſcarrying forbeareth Phyſicke, violent exerciſe, and many meates and drinkes, which otherwiſe ſhee might freely uſe: even ſo thoſe who travell in birth with the children of Chriſt, are put to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and abridge themſelves of many indifferences. I will eate no fleſh, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> while the world ſtandeth, rather than make my brother to offend, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.13.</p>
            <p>Reaſons enforcing their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence after an eſpeciall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from the appearances of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill are two: Becauſe in them
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:3506:74"/>they occaſion, firſt <hi>greater looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in bad ones:</hi> Secondly, <hi>more heavineſſe to good ones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt greater <hi>looſeneſſe in bad ones.</hi> Strange it is how the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and more ignorant ranke of men will be hereby ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their downeright ſinfull courſes: Nay if a Miniſter doe but wiſely and lawfully uſe his Chriſtian liberty, the rude vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar will thereupon open them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a gappe unto all licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. If he be but innocently pleaſant, thinke they wee may be mad, If hee but ſip, wee may carouſe. If hee ſpend but ſome few houres in his honeſt and harmeleſſe recreations, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon gameſter preſenly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes his miſpenſe of both time &amp; patrimony in gaming to be thence juſtifiable.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>more heavineſſe to good ones:</hi> it grieves the ſpirits of the righteous to ſee them in any, it wounds their ſoules, it makes their bloods, their hearts
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:3506:74"/>riſe to behold them in a man of God: it becomes not my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to adviſe, onely in mine owne and others behalfe, I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly wiſh and pray, that this were feriouſly thought upon, and preached by us all, that all of us in a tender regard to the reputation and humour of our high calling would walke with great circumſpection, make ſtraight ſteps unto our feete, tread every ſtep as nicely, as gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly as if wee went among ſnares, walk'd upon ropes, or pinnacles.</p>
            <p>I will conclude with that of <hi>Bernard</hi> to <hi>Eugenius, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de conſideratione, cap.</hi> 4. which though written particularly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, may yet fittingly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough be applyed to every mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, nay every Chriſtian. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt tuae perfectionis malas res, &amp; malas pariter ſpecies devita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, in altero conſcientiae in altero fame conſulis.</hi> It becomes your holineſſe to decline as evill
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:3506:75"/>things, ſo alſo evill appearances, in that thou conſult'ſt for thy conſcience, in this for thy ſame, nay (indeed) if it be not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption to adde unto the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in this thou provideſt both for conſcience and fame: for conſcience firſt; for the puritie, for the peace of thy conſcience; for the purity of thy conſcience, to keepe it void of offence both towards God, &amp; towards men; for the peace of thy conſcience, to preſerve it from the violence of Satans temptations, from the vexations of thine owne feares, and jealouſies. Secondly, for fame, ſo to hedge it in from ſcandall as that it ſhall be above the reach of ſuſpition. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to goe on in the words of the Father, <hi>Puta tibi non licere, etſi alias fortaſſe liceat, quidquid malè fuerit coloratum, non ſit in fama navus malae ſpeciei.</hi> Thinke not for thee lawfull, though perhaps otherwiſe lawfull, whatſoever ſhall be evill co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loured:
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:3506:75"/>In thy fame let there not be ſo much as a ſpot of evill appearance, ſo ſhalt thou fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low things that are of good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8. and thereby quite take off all private preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, all open calumnies againſt either thy perſon or profeſſion. However thou ſhalt procure the teſtimony and approbation of God and thine owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and be preſented unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, cleare from offenſiveneſſe before men, from faultineſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, at the appearing of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; to whom with the Father, &amp; holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed by us, and the whole Church, the Kingdome, the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and Glory, from this time forth for evermore.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:3506:76"/>
            <pb n="147" facs="tcp:3506:76"/>
            <head>THE POSTSCRIPT</head>
            <head type="sub">to the Reader.</head>
            <p>WHereas from page the 57. to page the 63. we delivered that according to the common opinion of the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, things commanded might in caſe of ſcandall be for a while omitted or forborne, <hi>Vaſquez</hi> and <hi>Becanus</hi> diſſent from us and them in this particular, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication and confirmation of their opinion I will briefly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, and then leave to thy cenſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Becanus,</hi> to make way for his opinion premiſeth that there is a difference betweene naturall precepts, for ſome ſaith he bind ſimply and alwayes whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver circumſtances intervene, and their obligation never ceaſeth, ſuch like are thoſe that forbid lying, perjury, hatred of God, Idolatrie, &amp;c: for theſe facts are ſo intrinſecally ſinfull, as that
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:3506:77"/>they cannot by any circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces bee made lawfull: others now bind not ſimply, and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, but with certaine cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and therefore they bind as long as thoſe circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances remaine, they ceaſe to binde when thoſe circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are changed: Such is the precept forbidding to kill, for that bindes with theſe circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, that we kill not by our private authoritie, except in caſe of neceſſary defence. Take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way theſe circumſtances, and it binds not, for it is lawfull to kill upon the command of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or in our neceſſary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: ſuch alſo is the precept of eſchewing ſcandall; for how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be dictated by the law of nature, yet it obligeth not <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely &amp; quomodocunque:</hi> but with certaine circumſtances, and one circumſtance neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to make it binde us, is that there occurre not any other precept, either naturall or poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:3506:77"/>The reaſon is, becauſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one is bound to have a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter care of his own than others ſalvation; and conſequently, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to avoid ſinne in himſelfe, than to prevent it in his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. And therefore that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept which is given us for the prevention of ſinne in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, is but of a ſecondary obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. Now the precept of eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewing ſcandall is impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, onely for the hindring of ſinne in others, and therefore doth not tye us when there oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curreth any other precept, which is given for the avoiding of ſinne in our ſelves. But it may be objected, that the precept of ſhunning ſcandall is of the law of nature, and therefore is more obligatory than thoſe precepts that are but poſitive. Unto this <hi>Becanus</hi> anſwereth, that a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall precept is more obligatory than that which is poſitive, <hi>cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris paribus,</hi> that is, if each pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept both that which is naturall,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:3506:78"/>and that which is poſitive, bee primarily referr'd unto the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of our owne ſalvation, unto the preventing of ſinne in our ſelves: but now if on the other ſide the primary ſcope of the naturall precept bee to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſinne in others, as it is in the precept of ſcandall, and the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall end of the poſitive pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept bee to ſhunne ſinne in our ſelves, than that precept which is poſitive doth more deeply binde us than that which is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall.</p>
            <p>Againe ſecondly, it may bee objected, that if the obligation of the naturall precept of eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewing ſcandall, ceaſeth upon occurrence of but a poſitive precept; why then it ſeemes this poſitive precept detracts or derogates from the naturall precept of avoiding ſcandall, as being of greater force and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity.</p>
            <p>In no wiſe, onely it takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way a circumſtance requiſite to
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:3506:78"/>make the precept of avoiding ſcandall obligatory, <hi>quale cum dicimus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Vaſquez</hi>) <hi>non eſſe omittendum praceptum poſitivu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> propter vitandum ſcandalum proximi, non dicimus praeceptum naturale derogare praecepto poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivo tanquam fortiori, ſed dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus occurſu praecepti poſitivi ceſſare quan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am circumſtantiam neceſſariam, ut obliget praeceptum de vitando ſcandalo etiamſi na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turale ſit.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:3506:79"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 7. l. 4. 5, for <hi>orthoxe</hi> read <hi>orthodoxe.</hi> l. 21. for <hi>is little</hi> r. <hi>is as little.</hi> p. 16. l. 14, for <hi>the</hi> r. <hi>unto the.</hi> p. 20. l. 25. for, <hi>diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting unto,</hi> r. <hi>diſsenting from, or aſſenting unto.</hi> p. 21. l. 16. for, <hi>an,</hi> r. <hi>and.</hi> p. 45. l. 5. for, <hi>peccata,</hi> r. <hi>peccato.</hi> p. 47. <hi>l.</hi> 4. for, <hi>with,</hi> r. <hi>without.</hi> p. 53. l. 16, 17. for, <hi>regall,</hi> r. <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular.</hi> p. 54. <hi>l.</hi> 13. for, <hi>charity limits,</hi> how r. <hi>charity, limits how</hi> p. 63. l. 4. for <hi>really, ſo a ſin,</hi> r. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> really ſo, a ſin.</hi> p. 70. l. ult. for, <hi>more</hi> r. <hi>nor.</hi> p. 72. l. 7. for, <hi>none,</hi> r. <hi>of none.</hi> p. 77. l. 12. for, <hi>hac,</hi> r. <hi>hoc.</hi> p. 86. l. 8, 9. for <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> r. <hi>ſuſpicion.</hi> p. 87. l. 2. for, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogically,</hi> r. <hi>Anagogically,</hi> pag. 105. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> l. 18. for <hi>vetere,</hi> r. <hi>vet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>res.</hi> p. 106. dele <hi>and.</hi> p. 107. l. 13. for, <hi>his,</hi> r. <hi>this.</hi> pag. 114. l. 10. dele, <hi>then.</hi> p. 116. l. 25. for, <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument</hi> r. <hi>Arguments.</hi> p. 129. l. 13. for, <hi>plano,</hi> r. <hi>plana.</hi> p. 131. l. 2. dele <hi>prima.</hi> p. 143. l. 7. for, <hi>preached,</hi> r. <hi>practiſed.</hi> &amp; l. 9. for, <hi>humor,</hi> r. <hi>honour.</hi> p. 148. l. 23. for, <hi>abſolutely,</hi> r. <hi>abſolute.</hi> p. 151. l. 2. for, <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le,</hi> r. <hi>quare.</hi> &amp; l. 7. for, <hi>der<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gare,</hi> r. <hi>der<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3506:79"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
